<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The firme foundation of Catholike religion, against the bottomles pitt of heresies wherin is shewed that only Catholiks shalbe saued, &amp; that all heretikes of what sect so euer are excluded from the kingdome of heauen. Compyled by Iohn Caumont of Champany: and translated out of French into English, by Iohn Pauncefote the elder Esquyre, in the tyme of his banishement.</title>
            <title>Du firmament des catholiques, contre l'abisme des heretiques. English.</title>
            <author>Caumont, Jean de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4868</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104922</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840652</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840652</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5177</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18250)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5177)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 526:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The firme foundation of Catholike religion, against the bottomles pitt of heresies wherin is shewed that only Catholiks shalbe saued, &amp; that all heretikes of what sect so euer are excluded from the kingdome of heauen. Compyled by Iohn Caumont of Champany: and translated out of French into English, by Iohn Pauncefote the elder Esquyre, in the tyme of his banishement.</title>
                  <title>Du firmament des catholiques, contre l'abisme des heretiques. English.</title>
                  <author>Caumont, Jean de.</author>
                  <author>Pauncefote, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 115, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Arnold Coninx,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Antwerpe :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.LXXXXI. [1591] Cum gratia &amp; priuileg. Reg. Maiest.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of Jean de Caumont's: Du firmament des catholiques, contre l'abisme des heretiques.</note>
                  <note>A1r line 5 of text ends "Christians,". Variant: quire A in another setting; A1r line 5 of text ends "christiās, &amp;".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5177:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:5177:1"/> THE FIRME FOVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DATION OF CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIKE RELIGION, AGAINST THE BOTTOMLES PITT OF HERESIES: wherin is ſhewed that only Catholiks ſhalbe ſaued, &amp; that all heretikes of what ſect ſo euer are excluded from the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compyled by</hi> IOHN CAVMONT <hi>of Champany: And tranſlated out of French into Engliſh, by</hi> IOHN PAVNCEFOTE <hi>the elder Eſquyre, in the tyme of his baniſhement.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Hoc habet authoritas matris Eccleſiae, hoc fundatus veritatis canon: contra hoc robur, contra hunc inexpugnabilem murum quiſquis arietat. ipſe confringitur.</p>
               <bibl>S. Auguſt. de verb. Apoſt. ſerm. 15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at Antwerpe by Arnold Coninx, M. D. LXXXXI.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum Gratia &amp; Priuileg. Reg. Maieſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="translation" type="license_to_print">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5177:2"/> HIS Catholike Maieſte hath graunted and giuen licens to Arnold Coninx, that he may print the booke named <hi>The firme foundation of the Catholike Religion againſt the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les pitt of hereſie,</hi> Tranſlated out of the french into Ingliſh by <hi>Iohn Paunſfote</hi> Eſquyer, vvhere in defence is made to all printers, for to print the ſame for the ſpace of three yeares, vvithout licence of the ſaid Arnold Coninx.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Geuen
<date>the 15. of Nouembre 1591.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Subſigned</hi> Io. de Buſchere</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translators_preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:5177:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE OF THE tranſlator.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it hath bene often a great greef vnto me to conſider hovv many of you (my deer frends and good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey men) not al of malice but ſome of blynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſome other of a folyſhe feare, others alſo for lak of inſtructions and trevv infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holy Catholike Church the true ſpouſe of Chriſt, do daylie erre and lyue in ſciſme &amp; hereſie, diuiding yor ſelues by that meanes from Chriſt his myſticall bodie, &amp; hazarding your ſoules to periſhe eternally: Euen ſo of late I did not a litle reioyce vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I hitt by chance on a litle frenche treatiſe, vvhich doth lyuelie expreſſe, &amp; as it vveare in a table ſett furth ſuch ſufficient, true, &amp; infallible tokens of Chriſt his Church, that none can be ignorant that is vvilling to learne, nor no man lefte in blyndnes that vvil open his eyes to ſee. And albeit my ſkylin the french tonge is but ſmall, yet the loue vvhich I beare to you my deare frendes hath ſupplied that vvant, and giueth me corage to attempt ſomthing aboue my ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth
<pb facs="tcp:5177:3"/> in tranſlating the ſayd treates as vvell as I could, vvhich I haue put to the print, that you may be partakers of it, truſting that you vvil accept the ſame as a token of my good vvill. And if it ſhall pleaſe God to ſend my labeur ſo good ſucceſſe, as that any of you all receiue benefit therby: after due thankes to him that is author of all goodnes, I pray you remember me in your deuout prayers, vvho haue not bene vnmyndfull of you here in this my poore baniſhement. And ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping you vvill excuſe or amend ſuch faultes as you may find eyther in the tranſlation or printyng. I beſeche God ſend you ſo much light, as to find the vvay home again to the Catholike Church. Fare you vvell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing frinde. I. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5177:3"/>
            <head>HE VVHO GA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THERETH NOT WITH ME, SCATTERETH ABRODE. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE FIRST principall &amp; moſt neceſſary grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of all <note place="margin">1.
<hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</note> woorke agreable to GOD, is, that it be done in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in vnion of Chriſtians, &amp; in the Catholike church: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohan.</hi> 1. 1.
<hi>Iohan.</hi> 2.</note> and all that man doth in the ſpirit of the Catholike church, is wel li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked before God: for that it is as it were dipped in the bloud of his welbeloued ſonne IESVS Chriſt, in whom he taketh his good pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: of whoſe grace and vnction all thoſe that be Catholikes be partakers, flowing from him vpon them as from the head vpon the members. Yea it is IESVS Chriſt him ſelf which liueth, which breatheth, which <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi>
15. <hi>Galat.</hi> 2. <hi>S. Auguſt. in Pſalm.</hi> 85. <hi>&amp; ſer.</hi> 4. <hi>de ſanct. Steph.</hi>
               </note> prayeth, and which ſturreth in all thoſe that be Catholikes and members of the body of his Church. <hi>He prayeth</hi> (ſaieth S. Auguſtin)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5177:4"/> 
               <hi>for vs, he prayeth in vs, and he is prayed to of vs, As</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vnus ipſe ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uator corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſui Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus noſter Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſtus filius Dei orat pro nobis, orat in nobis, &amp; orarur à nobis: vt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos noſter, orat pro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, vt caput noſtrum orat in nobis, vt Deus noſter oratur a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis.</note> 
               <hi>our Prieſt, be prayeth for vs: as our head, he prayeth in vs: and as our God, is prayed to of vs.</hi> This is the glory, the ioy, and aſſurance of a Catholike man, that Ieſus Chriſt is in him the chief agent, the which for his reuerence is heard of God in him: and this is the trew firmament of the Catholikes, more firme then the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it ſelf. It is not ſo in heretikes, all that which is of heretikes, is accurſed and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination before God: their faith, their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, their prayers, their faſtings, their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Ignat. ep. ad Heron. S. Io. Chryſ. ho.</hi> 65. <hi>in Ioan.</hi>
               </note> al actes of religion comyng from them are nothing els but curſed ſacriledge &amp; pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. If they ſhould raiſe vp the dead: if they ſhould be more vviſe then Angels: If they ſhould haue their faith ſo great as to moue mountaines: if they ſhould diſtribute <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Cypr. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de vni. Eccleſ. S. Auguſt. lib. de ſiide ad Pe.</hi>
               </note> all their goods to the cheriſhing of the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: if they ſhould kepe heroically continual virginitie: if they ſhould delyuer their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to be burned: if they ſhould ſhyne with an Angelical holines: all this ſerueth them for nothing being diuided from the body of the Church: al this vvould not any thing appeaſe the rigour of the eternal ire of God vpon them. Core, Dathan, and Abiron, did ſacrifice to the ſame God that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nuus.</hi> 16.</note> Moyſes did, yea to the only trew and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5177:4"/> God but for that it was done in diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the body of the Church, the earth did open and ſwalow them vp aliue, with their wiues, their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, their howſ holds, their Tabernacles, and all their ſubſtance: and more ouer, the fyer of God did conſume 250. of the chief that were aſſotiated with them, and 14700. of the people, for that they murmured at that iuſtice: And the fury of Gods wrathe had conſumed all the people wholy, but for the vehement interceſſion and meditation of the Prieſthood of Aaron which did appeaſe the ſame. God doth not receaue ſacrifice but of his Prieſtes whom he hath ordayned for that purpoſe, and there is no ſeruice what ſo euer agreable to God but that of the children of his Church.</p>
            <p>Let not the heretike flatter him ſelf with the holy ſcriptures, as peruerſe men do abuſe all the gyftes of God, employing them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then they be ordeyned by his prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: ſo do they abuſe the holy ſctiptures them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. That hath bene alwayes the cloke of impietie of heretikes, <hi>they carie againſt Ieſus Christ, the ſigne of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> ſayth S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Aug. ep.</hi> 16. Contra Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum portant ſignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium, de ipſo Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio gloria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur.</note> and take holde of the Goſpel to make engines to fight againſt it. The Arrians would not agree to any one point, if it were not expreſly in the ſcripture. The Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5177:5"/> pretend the goſpel to make for them, and alleage the ſame for their ſoueraigne aucthoritie. The deuil him ſelf hath cyted the ſcripture againſt our ſauiour, and thereof it is that he prepareth ſnares and cordes to ſtrangle ſuch as harken to him, making that which ſhould bring them life, to be deadly vnto them, and conuerting bread in to poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. It is certain that the ſcripture is giuen vs of God for our ſaluation: &amp; this principle can not be ſhaken. When the holy ſcripture ſpeaketh, it is the maieſty of God which doth ſhew his truth and his wil vnto men, vnto the which euery man muſt beare inuiolable reuerence, and yeld vnto it as to the aſſured and infallible verditt of God his truth, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting all his vnderſtanding to the yoke and obedience of faith: in ſuche ſorte, that it is treaſon to God his maieſty and damnable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege for the boldnes of humaine vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to gaynſay the ſame, yea or only to be ſo bolde as to thinke it: for if any one gainſay the ſame, he cutteth him ſelf from God, and maketh him ſelf a companion of the deuil: he is an heretike, accurſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, &amp; neuer ſhall haue parte with God. For the holy ſcripture is the key which doth open vs Paradiſe: it is the way which doth guyde vs, the rule which doth teache vs, the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5177:5"/> lampe which doth ligten vs in the middeſt oft he darknes of this world: it is the looking glaſſe where in we behold the face of God, the royall ſceptre by the which he doth Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne his people, the witnes of his good wil towards vs, and the inſtrument of his alian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce: to the vvhich vvho ſo doth not bowe downe his vnderſtanding, he doth oppoſe him ſelf againſt God, with an ingratitude &amp; deueliſh preſumption. Now al the heretikes of the vvorld haue made ſhew to agree to this principle, &amp; haue whyted their ruinouſe walles with no other colours than thoſe, nor haue no other thing in their mouthes but the texts of the ſcriptures. What ſhal the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple man then doe, hearing the word of the maieſty of God in the mouth of Catholikes and of heretikes? This is it whereof I wold informe ſuch as haue care of their ſaluation, and teach them how they ſhal neuer be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued. S. Gregor Nazianzene ſayth that <note place="margin">In Orat. ad Athanaſ.</note> the ſcripture is like vnto certaine paynted Images, which what way ſo euer you turne you, you thinke their eye foloweth you; yet notwithſtanding, the right looke doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in ſome one point to the workman in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, &amp; thoſe that are cunnyng in that arte know it very well. Likewiſe the holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is to be taken in many ſenſes, and farre
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5177:6"/> more then the ſcriptures of men: for ſo much as the ſcriptures do participate of the nature of the author. But ſo it is that God him ſelf is the author of the holy ſcriptures: whoſe vnderſtanding being infinite, the ſenſe of his ſcriptures may be alſo infinite. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding there is one proper ſenſe, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, &amp; aſſured in the ſcriptures, whiche the holie Ghoſt hath vouchſafed to reueale vnto men, which is the ſenſe of the Goſpel, that is to ſay, the right, trew, and natural ſenſe of the voyce of the Prophets and the Apoſtles, which is in effect the goſpel. For properly the Goſpel doth not conſiſt in figures of letters and dead characters of the writing of the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſts: Thoſe thinges be but as an Image of the ſenſe of the Goſpel. But wil you know what is properly the goſpel? It is the ſolemne publication of the ſonne of God deſcended from the boſom of his father, and ſhewed in fleaſh for to delyuer mankynd from the ſtate of perdition in which he was, and to reconcile him to God: geuing power to the children of Adam, which beleeue in his name, to be made children of God, rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing them in him ſelf, and regenerating them to God by diuine Sacraments, by the which he hath made them partakers of his iuſtice, of his life, and of his glory, and hath
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5177:6"/> lifted them vp with him from changeable time to the eternitye of his father. S. Paul doth define the Goſpel, to be <hi>the mighty povver</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi>
1.</note> 
               <hi>of God to ſaluation, to al thoſe that beleue:</hi> that is to ſay, a vertu ſupernatural, diuinely infuſed, ennobling mans nature aboue it ſelf, and eleuating it to a diuine eſtate, the which of his owne force and faculty he could neuer attayne vnto, no not only conceiue the ſame: <note place="margin">Lab. de prapa. Euang.</note> it is ſayeth Euſebius, that Goſpel which doth ſhew the reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of goods, not theſe earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, periſhable, &amp; which do decay, but of the true, ſoueraigne, diuine, euerlaſting, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible goods promiſed from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the world, and foretold of all the Prophetes, &amp; that which doth giue the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to get them. To be ſhort, the Goſpel is a nevv reſurrection of the worlde, and as it is ſayd in the Godſpel it ſelfe, it is the ſeed of eternitie. All the matter is to knovve vvho be the true ſovvers, and diſpenſators of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Goſpel, that be ſent and auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched of God. For God doth not auouche all thoſe vvhich thruſt them ſelues into this diuine embaſſage, he hath ſayd to the vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: vvho gaue the charge to rehearſe my iuſtices &amp; take my teſtament in thy mouth? And he complayneth him ſelfe in Ezechiel, of falſe Prophetes vvhich runne vvithout <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 49.
<hi>Ezech.</hi> 13.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:5177:7"/> ſendinge. <hi>They runne</hi> ſayth he, <hi>and I ſent them not, they ſay the lorde hath ſayd it, and I ſayd no ſuch worde.</hi> Our ſauiour him ſelfe by his
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.</note> holy mouth doth aduertiſe vs ſaying: <hi>Take heede of falſe Prophets which come to you in ſheeps clothing, but within they are rauening wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues.</hi> Now if in the traficke of this world, we feare to medle with a falſe marchant, how much more owght vve to feare in the traficke of euerlaſting ſaluation. If then vve vvil not be deceaued, Sainct Paule therein doth geue vs a true meane, vvhen he ſayth: <hi>How ſhal they beleue in him whom</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>they haue not hearde? And how ſhal they heare without preaching? And how ſhal they preach yf they be not ſent?</hi> There neede not ſo much diſputing, nor ſo much making of bookes, to confound the heretikes. Men do in a maner defile them ſelues vvhen they exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne their doctrine: there is no doute but that God is greatly offended with the ouermuch regarde that is geuen vnto them, and thoſe which wolde that men ſhulde heare them reaſon, haue not the ſpirit of the feare of God. An heretike, before all other thinges ſhould be aſked not what he ſayth, but of whom he is ſent, and the marke of his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. And ſo without any more diſputing he ſhal be confounded and put to ſilence. For
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5177:7"/> neuer heretike was ſent of God, they are al of the ſpirit of the deuil, and al condemned of God, what allegation ſo euer they make of the holie ſcriptures. The Samaritanes were heretiques, and did fortifie them ſelues with the texte of the law of Moyſes. Our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour hath condemned them with his owne mouth, when being aſked of the Samaritane whether God ſhould be worſhipped in Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem or in Samaria, he anſwered: <hi>you worſhippe that you know not, wee worſhipp that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohan.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>we knowe: the ſaluation is of the Jewes.</hi> For it is as yf he had ſayd yow Samaritanes which be diſtracted from the Iewes, you ſhal haue nothing in the treaſure of ſaluation, and you can not but erre. This only voice thundering from heauen, <hi>you worſhipp that you know not,</hi> is a ſufficient flaſh of lightening to ouerthrow all that theſe deuided felowes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Curch can imagine to haue, eyther holie or godlie. Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ouertake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the deuil through ignorance of this doctrine. S. Auguſtin teacheth vs clearly: that although heretikes <note place="margin">S. Auguſt. in Enchrid. ad Lauren.</note> do preache the name of Ieſus Chriſt, yet that name is not their ſeur grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as it is to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, but remayneth proper to the Church only: for if one conſyder aduyſedly that which belongeth to Ieſus Chriſt; he ſhall not fynde it amongſt heretikes what ſo euer,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5177:8"/> but in tytle and ſhew only: the effect of the vertue ſhal not be there: they ſound out with full mouth, that they holde the ſonne of God for the redeemer of the worlde, but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng after they haue pronounced thoſe woords, becauſe they ſpoyle hym of his vertue &amp; dignitie, that which S. Paule ſayth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Colloſ.</hi>
2.</note> is truly proper vnto them: <hi>that they keepe not the heade, whereof the whole body</hi> (which is the Church) <hi>by ioyntes &amp; bandes being compacted, groweth to the increaſe of God.</hi> And according to this, Optatus properly ſayth that the buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Opt. li.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.</note> of heretykes is but only a wal which hath no corner ſtone nor couerture aboue, in ſuch ſorte that if they make a gate, he that entreth in, is alwayes without, ſubiect to wyndes, rayne, tempeſt, theeues, and to wylde beaſts. But the Catholike Church is an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier howſe in the which God doth dwel, and he dwelleth not in any other. Al that which is incloſed therein, is couerd, wel aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, &amp; out of daunger: of the incommody<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of the ayre, of theeues, and of all external harme. Furthermore he compareth hereſie to artificial trees, which fowlers faſhion in likenes of a natural tree, hauing the ſhew of a true tree, but full of ſnares and of glew, where the brides ſearching their life, fynde their death: wheras the Church is a true
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5177:8"/> tree in deed, full of good fruits, without ſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and fraude. But aboue al. S. Cyprian hath very wel ſayd that hereſie and idolatrie be in <note place="margin">Lib. de vnit. Eccleſ.</note> the ſame damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as daughters of the ſame father: when (ſayth he) by the coming of Ieſus Chriſt, the light being reuealed vnto the gentiles, and the ſonne of ſaluation ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the face of al people, the darknes of idolatry was chaſed out of the world, Satan ſeing his ſeates and temples deſolate, and his Idols forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al people on te earth, which did runne vnto the Churches of Ieſus Chriſt, he found a new craft vnder the ſelf ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of Chriſtian, to intangle them that were not wel aduiſed, and to make them fal from the grace of Ieſus Chriſt: that is, he hath ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp hereſies, with the which he hath ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted the fayth, corrupted the truth, and broken the vnite of concorde: in ſuch ſorte that thoſe whom he can not longer hold in the auncient way of blyndnes, he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued by the error of a new way<hi>:</hi> &amp; ſo ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth men euen within the Church, deceauing them with an other kynd of darkenes, to the end that not contynewing in the vnitye of the Church, they may yet cal them ſelues Chriſtians, and walking in darkens, they may perſwade them ſelues to haue the light: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them blinde without perceauing their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5177:9"/> blyndes, yea then when they thinke them ſelues moſt ſure of the light. For as he is a cunnyng woorkeman to transforme him ſelf often into an Angel of light, he leadeth them in to likelihoodes of truth, that he may ſo deceiue them in the truth: affirmyng the night for day, death for life, infidelitye for faith, Antichriſt vnder the name of Ieſus Chriſt. And ther is not any abſurditye how monſtrous and foule ſo euer it be, that he doth not make them receyue, and that very greedelye, and hauing once bleared them with his iugling tricks, he holdeth theyr iudgements ſo faſt tyed and hampered, that they can not ſee the very open and manyfeſt truth: ſo that hauing now no more roote in God, they be caſt into a reprobate ſenſe, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to their owne deſtruction al that is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto them, and ſticke not now to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and fyght agaynſt God him ſelf. Now, to them wich ſuffer them ſelues to be deceiued, it happeneth (ſayeth S. Cyprian) for not ſearching the truth of faith by the right way, according to the direction of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Maiſter, who doth ſend vs to the chayer of S. Peter, which of his proper auctoritie by prerogatyue he hath ordeined to be head, &amp; as the fountayne &amp; roote of his Church. And this was a greate benefit of God, that he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5177:9"/> hath giuen a certaine ſeat to his Church, as auncyently was the chayre of Moyſes, to the end that in the doubtful points of faith, men myght haue a place to reſorte vnto, as to a certeine Vniuerſite, to receiue their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſo to kepe the vnitie of faith among ſo many dyuers nations that were to enter in to the Church.</p>
            <p>This is certeinly the point whereby all heretikes in the world haue periſhed, doe periſhe now, and ſhall alwayes periſhe: for that they like not, not ſauour not the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the vnitie of faith in the vniuerſal bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therhood of the Church, nor acknowledge that there is one certain Church, the only mother of al the children of God, which is only holie, Catholike, and Apoſtolike: vnto whom Ieſus Chriſt her ſpouſe &amp; head hath giuen the character of the order of his eternall Prieſthood, the keyes of the realme of heauen, &amp; all aucthoritie ouer his howſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould: vnto whom he hath promiſed aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his holie ſpirit vntil the end of the worlde: in whom is the wil of God, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of ſinnes, and the diſtribution of graces: who only hath the woord of God in keeping, the pure doctrine of the Goſpell, the true vſe of Sacraments: to whom only there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth appertain to iudge of the true
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5177:10"/> ſenſe of the holy ſcriptures, and to decyde the controuerſies of faith that riſe among men: whoſe iudgements in earth be ratified in heauen: which Church, being but one and vndiuided in faith, yet extending it ſelf in her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the beames of the ſunne, as long and as wyde as the whole world, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſinge &amp; multiplyinge dayly without end or lymit, continueth inſeparably vnited to her head, as the beames to the body of the ſunne, not liuinge but of his grace, not brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but of his ſpirit, and not ſeing but of his light: and who ſo euer kepeth not this vnitie, he kepeth not the law of God, he hath no faith, and he can neyther haue the life nor the ſaluation of Ieſus Chriſt. It is S. Paul him <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.</note> ſelf that teacheth this Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the vnitie of faith in the vniuerſalitie of the Church: as there is not (ſaith he) but one ſole God, lord &amp; father of all, ſo there is but one faith, one hope, one truſt, one bodie, one ſpirit: the head of which bodie, is the ſonne of God Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who being him ſelf the ſpring of lyfe euerlaſting, doth inſpire lyfe to all the bodie, &amp; doth furniſh it dayly with ſtrength by his holy ſpirit. Whoſoeuer is not a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that bodie, can not take lyfe of the ſpirit of Ieſus Chriſt: he is a ſtraunger: he is prophaned: he is an enemie, he is dead, drye
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5177:10"/> and wythered without moyſture of all diuine grace, and that no part of the promiſes and rewards of Ieſus Chriſt: he is the braunche <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohan.</hi>
11.</note> cut from the true ſtocke, appointed to the fyer to be burned. If any of thoſe which were out of the Arcke of Noe vvere ſaued, thoſe alſo ſhal be ſaued which are founde out of the Arke of the Church. If the riuer cut from his ſpring dryeth not vp: if the braunche di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided from the tree can bear fruit: if the member cut from the bodie can take lyfe of the ſame bodie: then alſo the man that is diuided and cut from the Church, ſhal liue of Ieſus Chriſt. He can not haue God for his father, which wil not haue the Church for his mother: and he can not be vnited with God, which is not vnited with the Church. At the ſame inſtant that man doth ſeparat him ſelf fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church, he dyeth from Ieſus Chriſte, and leeſeth the grace of the holy Ghoſt. For euen as the vniuerſal ſenſible light is tyed to the bodie of the ſunne which doth ſpread and diſtribute it to all the world, in the abſence wherof, there is nothing but darknes: euen ſo al grace of reconciliation to God, was annexed to the bodie of Ieſus Chriſt: yea to this bodie of his which dayly groweth by increaſe of the choſen, preordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to lyfe euerlaſting, which is the bodie
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5177:11"/> of the Church, which he doth gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, taking out from the heape of mankynd al men of good wyl, which haue bene, are, and ſhal be, to the end of the world: out of which bodie there is but the wrath and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lediction of God. Search where you wil: out of this Church, you ſhall fynde nothing but death. To be ſhort, he which is not in the Church hath no God: he hath his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per iudgement, his phantaſie, and his owne preſumption for his God: he maketh him ſelfe an Idol, &amp; doth worſhip only his owne imagination in place of God. If ſuch a man calleth him ſelf a Chriſtian, that is as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil often ſayth he is Chriſt: and if he be kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for his hereſie, that is no martirdom, bur the reward of his hereſie, which is not yet al purged by his owne death. Dying he goeth to yeld and ioyne him ſelf eternally to the darkenes, which he hath worſhiped; and to his head which is the deuil. There is no martirdom nor death pretious before God but in the catholique Church: in the which only is the grace of the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt: the which only ſhe doth preach in ſinceritie and truth, and without any hazard or poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie to erre<hi>:</hi> becauſe ſhe taketh her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the holy Ghoſt, &amp; of the tradition of the Apoſtles, and of the holy ſcriptures
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5177:11"/> together: which be the three grounds ſet downe by the holy ſcripture it ſelf: the which doth ſhew that not ſhee only buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vp the Churche, but is alſo holpen of the traditions of the liuely voyce of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, to the which ſhe often tymes refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth men. <hi>Kepe</hi> (ſayeth S. Paul) <hi>the traditions</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2.
<hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. Tenete tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones quas didiciſtis, ſiue per ſermone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſiue per epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Act.</hi> 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16</note> 
               <hi>which you haue learned of me, be it by woord or by our epiſtle:</hi> and it is written in the Actes of the Apoſtles that in al places whear S. Paule paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by, he recommended to the Churches, <hi>to kepe the ordinances of the Apoſtles and of the elders,</hi> which were things not written. When the Apoſtles had planted the Goſpel, they did not ſay al things at one time, nor in one howre: nor wrote al that they ſayed: but according as occaſion was giuen, they planted their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: ſo that the holy ſcripture which we haue of the Apoſtles and of the Euangeliſts, is not ſo muche a full doctrine of faith, as a witnes of the faith that they preached. Now if wee will goe higher: the law of Moyſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted no leſſe in tradition than in writting: and not only the ſenſe but the letter and text thereof was to be learned by tradition. For they had the ſcriptures in maner but by half: the pointing beeing not yet put to the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew text. But the holy Ghoſt alwayes hath in formed the Church of the true traditions
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5177:12"/> and the true ſenſe of the ſcripture, in ſuch ſorte as the Church and the holy ſcripture are ſo linked together, that they both be as an indiſſoluble cheyne of golde. The Church is not aboue the ſcripture, but the authoritie of the Church doth ſhew the true ſcripture. And when the Church hath need of wholſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me information, ſhe doth goe to the ſcripru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: and if there be any darknes in the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, the holy Ghoſte is giuen to the Church for to interpret the ſame. Euen ſo in the olde law in al difficulties, that roſe, the law of Moyſes ordained that they ſhould goe to the hygh prieſt for the tyme being, and that they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. <hi>Malach.</hi> 2.</note> ſhould folow his verdit, not turnyng either to the right ſyde or the left, vpon paine of death. The Prophets alſo ſent them thether, and in the Goſpel it ſelf our ſauiour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, that if any obey not the Church, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.</note> he be degraded from the name of Chriſtian, and holden for an Eathnike: let no man now ſeeke excuſes in a corner. God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed at al tymes the prieſts of the Church preſent, to iudge the preſent controuerſies: and willeth that men ſhould repayre vnto them: his holy ſpirit aſſiſteth them to that end. He hath not promiſed vs in them more then in other men, example of holynes: but he hath promiſed vs by them the Oracles of
<pb facs="tcp:5177:12"/> his truthe. Oh that al thoſe that do erre in faith did know the vertue of the name Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, and the horror of the name hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke: how the Catholique in his faith, doeth renounce his own reaſon, his own iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, his vnderſtanding, his wil, and all his ſenſes, for to hearken ſimplie and abſolutely vnto that that the Church doth teache: how on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie ſide, the heretike doth grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; builde his fayth vpon his owne iudgement. They ſhould knowe that the name Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, is a name of repoſe in God: a name vtterlie denying him ſelfe, to the end he may be ouerwhelmed in God: and that to leane and ſtaie vpon the Church, is to leane and ſtaie vpon God him ſelfe: and that contrarie wiſe to ſtaye vpon him ſelfe, that is to ſay vpon his owne iudgement, is to ſtay him ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe vpon the deuil: they ſhould knovve that the Church teacheth the people faythfully, and that ſhe is aſſiſted of the holie Ghoſt: that ſhe hath the trevve traditions of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: and doth take the ſcripture in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelical ſenſe; ſayeth nothing of her ſelfe, putteth nothing of nevve, dothe not make any article of fayth: but only giueth vvitnes of the Euangelical ſenſe, and diſcerneth the good from the euil paſture, euen as the holy Ghoſt doth reueale to her in common.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5177:13"/> And contraryvviſe that the heretike is not ſtirred but of his ovvn particular ſpirit: hath not any tradition but of his owne proper ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: taketh the ſcripture in a ſenſe by him ſelf inuented: handling the ſame as if him ſelf were the authour: making him ſelf a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to hym ſelf, and iudge of God: and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes ſetteth him ſelf aboue al that which is God: in ſom much that he doth iudge by his owne priuate ſenſe, the eternal woord of God: in ſuch ſort as al hereſie maketh a new paradox, &amp; putteth a new ſenſe, neuer Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelized, not of the holy Ghoſt, but inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of Satan, by the mouth of one particular man. The ſpirit of God is not particular, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: and the ſame is in common to the Church, to whom hath bene giuen the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the holy Ghoſt, to ſhew vnto her al truthe: in ſuch ſorte, that, as it is certein that the holy Ghoſt is authour of the ſcripture: ſo is it certein that the holy Ghoſt is the ſoule and lyfe of the Church, by whoſe direction ſhe can neuer erre, for which cauſe S. Paul doth cal her <hi>the piller and ground of trueth.</hi> And <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> this is it that S. Auguſtin did confeſſe, <hi>o lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Auguſt. lib.</hi> 12.
<hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſ. c.</hi> 25</note> (ſayeth he) <hi>thy trueth is not myne, nor this mans, or that mans: but it is euerie mans, whom thou pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blikly</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Veritas tua eſt domine no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mea, nec il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, aut illius; ſed omnium noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quos ad co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mem publice vocas, terribi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ne priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam veritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habeamus ne priuemut ea. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 8.</note>
               <hi>calleſte to the communion therof, warnyng vs terribly that we take greate heed to chalenge that</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:5177:13"/> 
               <hi>in priuate, leſt ſo we be vtterlie depriued of it. For he which ſpeaketh of his owne telleth a lye.</hi> And as many particular opinions as are in the world, ſo many banners are there diſplayed by the deuil. A true catholique doth eſtrange him ſelf as much as he can from all particular opinions, and from al attributing to him ſelf, his being, his liuing, his power and knowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, and neuer doth vſe theſe termes: <hi>I am: I can, I wil, as for me, this is my opinion,</hi> and ſuch like ſpeches, which be termes of deueliſh ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie. He dares not ſo much as to ſay of him ſelf that he is a part of Chriſtendom, ſtanding as it wear by him ſelf alone: but hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this for a principle that he can not ſo much as thinke any thing, that good is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout the continual dependence of God, and inſtruction of the Church: vnto whom in all ſimplicitie, and in deep humlitie, he leaueth him ſelf to be edified and inſtructed, euen as a litle childe of his mother: ſo that it is in a maner eaſier to plucke a ſterre out of the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than to plucke a true catholique out of the boſome of the Churche. Litle Iacob when Rebecca his mother commanded him to faigne him ſelf to his father that he was Eſau, to get thereby his bleſſing, he anſwered like a childe, that
<q>he feared leſt the deceit being diſcoueced, he ſhould procure hym</q>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:5177:14"/> ſelf malediction in ſtead of benediction: but then his mother ſayd to him,
<q>that maledictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 27.</note> (my ſonne) be vpon me: only obay thou my voyce in that I commaund the:</q> which he did, and was bleſt: euen ſo it is in our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Church. If the Church ſhould deceiue vs, then vpon her be the maledictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to vs doth apperteyn the glory of obedience, with the which we be very wel aſſured to obteyn the euerlaſting benediction. But now the Church can not deceiue vs, yea I ſay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the iniquite of him that is in the Church, is better, that is to ſay, is leſſe da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable then the good works of him which is in hereſie. For if one of the howſhold of the Church haue ſinned, he hath but committed that ſinne wherein he is fallen: the which is blotted out by pennance in the Churche, and he may obtein the promiſſes of the kyngdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of heauen: but he which is fallen out of the Church, ſinneth alwayes, &amp; in al that he doth: for al that which is not of faith, is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, as S. Paul ſaith. Yea although he do pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce yet ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he obtein no pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe in the ſocietie where he is, there is no remiſſion of ſinnes: there is no good worke meritorius, no pennance, no vertue to be rewarded wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the life euerlaſting where faithe is not: and that perſone dothe not fruitfully fulfil any comaundement of God which doth not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5177:14"/> the ſame in the Church. The pretended good works of thoſe which be out of the Church, be like a ſwyft running out of the way, and lyke great paynes taken for a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of nothing, where no reward is to be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. He which runneth out of the liſtes, ſhal neuer carie away the price: he muſt be firſt with in the barriers of the Church, ſeing that the courſe of good woorkes ſhal be crowned according to the merits of the rightuouſnes of eache one: I meane according as euery one ſhal ſhevv hymſelf valiant and couragious in chriſtian ſpirit, and according as the new regenerat man in him hathe brought foorth due fruits, and effects of his regeneration. There is no good without the ſoueraign good. The ſoueraign good, is God. God, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and the Churche, are three things coherent and faſt vnited together. There is no acceſſe to God, but by Ieſus Chriſt: and there is no acceſſe to Ieſus Chriſt, but by the Churche: let no man (ſayeth S. Ambroſe) accept good woorks, done before faith. Faith is the ſoule of good woorkes, without the which they be dead, and be not to be rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with lyfe euerlaſting: faith is the ſoule of our ſoule, the ſubſtance of man, in ſuch ſorte as man without faith is without ſubſtance. True it is that an heretyke renouncing his hereſie is ſtraight wayes cleane, and incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5177:15"/> againe to the Church, and as a member, partaker of the prayers of all the vniuerſal Church, he is made woorthy of the body of Ieſus Chriſt, after he hath purelie and entier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie renounced his hereſie: in which caſe a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh. Clim. grad.</hi>
15.</note> fornicator repenting hath need of teares &amp; of tyme to be throughly clenſed, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh vtterly the concupiſcence which hath occupied the ſoule, and defiled the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the reliques of the one being harder to be healed, then of the other: but if the one and the other die in their ſinne, the heretike ſhal carie a more rigorous iudgement than the fornicator. This point then is without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction that in all the vniuerſal vvorld, there is but one only Church, vvhich doth adminiſter eternal lyfe: vvhich hath the keyes of the kyngdome of heauen: in vvhich good deeds be revvarded vvith lyfe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: vvhich dravving out of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the right line of interpretation both prophetical and Apoſtolical according to the ſenſe that hath bene preached and taught, geueth her children aſſured certentie of the good paſture, &amp; knowledge of the euil: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who ſo obeyeth not, ſhal neuer ſee God. For this cauſe S. Paul according to the care vvhich he had more then fatherly of the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of men, doth exhorte very earneſtly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5177:15"/> to be carefull, to kepe the vnitie of ſpirit: which is to hold them ſelues, ioint, firme, and locked in the boſome of the Churche: knowing that euerie where out of the ſame dwelleth death, and that euerie particular aſſemblie out of the ſame is the Synagog of Sathan. All diuinitie out of the Church is vaine, falſe, baſterdly, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſe, ful of deceit &amp; impietie. When the heretike alleageth woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the Goſpel that is now no more (ſaieth S. Hierom) the Goſpel of God. The Goſpel in their mouth becometh the woord of man, and the woord of the deuil: the trueth is poyſoned by their leauen, in ſuche ſorte that it is altogether vnlike to it ſelfe: wherin they fare as the falſe and leud counſeilors of a prince or ſtate, whoe in giuing counceil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounding to ther owne particular profit, and not of the Prince or common welth, doo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the Prince and the comon welthe: euen ſo, the heretiks be traitors to God and to the holy ſcriptures. And let no man be deceiued if ſomtimes they ſeeme to teach the ſame doctrine that the catholikes do: betwene the true and the falſe there is but a hears diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. But now ſuppoſe they preached in all &amp; throughout, the ſelf ſame doctrine of faith and Sacraments, as the catholiques doe:
<q>that they be alſo otherwiſe irreprehenſible of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5177:16"/> their life in external honeſtie: yea finallie though they ſpend their bloud for the name of Ieſus Chriſt: all this notvvithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, fith <note place="margin">S. Aug. lib. de fide ad petro.</note> they make a bodye apart, and hold not the vnitie of the catholike Church they be in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of perdition.</q> The vſe of the Sacraments, the woorks of mercie, and the gloriouſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the name of Ieſus Chriſte can not profit but vnto him which is in the vnitie of the catholique Church. Which vnitie who holdeth not, he diuideth the body of Ieſus Chriſt, which is one and indiuiſible: and his Church hath not two bodyes.
<hi>Ieſus Chriſt is not diuided</hi> (ſayth S. Paul) and that point is of ſo great importance as the creed of the faith, which is dayly ſonge in the Church doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely ſhew that there is but one Church to the end that all men might know that out of the ſame there is no ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Such as come near the brinke of a deep pit, or of any dovvneright pitche, conceiuing the horrour of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral death, all trembling they retier far of, for fear to fall therin: but there is not any deep pit or dovvneright pitche or peril vvhat ſo euer in this vvorld vvherein a man ſhould conceiue ſo much feare to fall as into hereſie. For in all hereſie dvvelleth the horrour of eternall death: And to fall from the aſſured firmament of the Churche in to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5177:16"/> hereſie, is to fall from cleaning to God to the bottomles pit of him ſelf: vvhich is as the fall of Satan, vvhen he vvas headlonge throvven dovvne from heauen to hell. Let vs then take heed God Chriſtian people of ſeparating of our ſelues, hovv litle ſo euer it be, from the catholike Church, no, not in one only litle thought: let vs yeeld vniuerſallie to all that the Church doth teach, vvithout reſeruing any thing, vvhat ſoeuer it be, to our particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar iudgement, againſt the iudgement of the Church. Looke hovv much any man reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to his ovvn reſolution, vpon his ovvn proper ſenſe, in matters of faith: ſo nigh he is to the loſſe of his lyfe, ſo farre is he in darknes of errour, ſo near is he to death, ſo much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided from God, ſo faſt cleaueth he to the deuil. Farre from all thoſe vvhich haue care of their ovvn euerlaſting ſaluation be that deadlie preſumption, vvhich would ſhare his faith vvith the Church: that is, vvould make a choiſe and particular ſeparation of the points vvhich it pleaſeth him to beleeue, or not to beleeue vvith the Church: as if that ſyde vvhereunto, by our ovvn direction, vve reſolue to leane, vvere to vs a better euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and cleeret teſtimonie than the vniuerſal Churche. This is, in verie deed to cenſure the Church and to make our ſelues iudges of
<pb facs="tcp:5177:17"/> the Church, and of the holy Ghoſt alſo, vvhich teacheth her. This is to be too too much ignorant of our own ignorance, vvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes, and meſure of our ovvn ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. The iudgement of one particular ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hovv vviſe ſo euer he may be, is but as a litle candle in the darknes of the night, the which giueth light ſcant fovver or fiue paſes in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, but is inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinent obſcured &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uironed with the exceding force of vniuerſal darknes. Wher
<hi>the Church,</hi> (vvhich, as S. Iohn ſayeth, <hi>is clothed with the ſunne, hauing the moon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>vnder her feet)</hi> dothe caſt her beames vpon the face of the vvhole earth, taking her brightnes from aboue, and drawing her light out of the ſea of the <hi>Intelligence diuine.</hi> Avvay (ſay I) vvith this preſumption: farre be it from all our friends: farre from the choſen and elect of God: farre from al thoſe, vvho haue an earneſt deſire of their ovvn ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; wolde vvillinglie forſake this worlde, to ſee God eternallie, and to attain vnto the glori of eternal felicitie. Avvay vvith this raſhenes of particularities in opinions ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the Church. This is the verie cockle of wicked ſpirits. This is the vvay to fall in to the hands of the deuil: vvho being not able to wound a man to death, by making him to forſake the Church abſolutelie, dothe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5177:17"/> yet vvound and disfigure the integritie, and ſincere purenes of a Chriſtian, in this point at leaſt, that novv he is not ſound, and ſincere, nor ſuch a one as the beautie and ſtate of a chriſtian requireth. <hi>Deformed is that member</hi> (ſayth S. Auguſtin) <hi>which is not conformable to the whole.</hi> Raither ſuffer the ſoule to be diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note place="margin">Auguſt. Turpis eſt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis pars vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſo ſuo non congruens.</note> from the bodie, with all the torments in the worlde, than to be diuided from the Church, or
<q>to diſſent from the Church in any one iote only, or in any one ſole litle point. He that would agree with the Church in all, except one only point, is not a catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. Faith is more indiuiſible than the beames of the ſunne: it is not to be holden by halues: it is a gift of God, and a grace infuſed: and the gifts of God are perfite.</q> For concerning faith, who ſo euer faileth in one article is cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable in all. And he is no leſſe drouned, which is but two fingars ouer head in water, than he which is an hundred fathoms dieper. A mans faith, eye, and honour, are thre things that can not endure to be hurt or impared, how litle ſoeuer it be. Many of them which haue yet ſome liuelie roote in the Church, and hate hereſie, doe giue to them ſelfes ſome times libertie to blame or contemne certein obſeruances and ceremonies of the Church, as in their opinions vnprofitable.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:5177:18"/> Theſe lo do daungerouſlie erre, beſides that they ſhew herein their beaſtlines, and ignorance: for nothing vniuerſallie receiued in the Church is of ſmall conſequence, or importance. And vnwoorthie are they to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue any place in the Church, and to be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the Sacraments of euerlaſting life, which doe diſagree with her in the leaſt point that a man can think of. Men ought with more reuerence to iudge of ſuch things as are approued and alowed of the vniuerſal Church. When men debate of humain mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, let then humain reaſon take place: but in the doctrine of faith, the only authoritie of the Churche ought to rule. It is not for vs to take vpon vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme, and eſtabliſh that whereunto we muſt obey. We muſt in al ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelues wholie to her iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception of any thing, what ſoeuer it be: For ſo ſoone as faith is ſeuered from the Sanctuarie of the Church, ſhe is out of her natural element: ſhe hath no more vital ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. The Church hath ſecret motiues, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations tending to the vtilitie and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of her vniuerſal familie, incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible to any one priuate perſon<hi>:</hi> yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they haue theyr foundacions and grounds verie firme and ſure. The moſt excellent Philoſophie that euer was in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5177:18"/> worlde, is that of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> which <hi>Philo</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.
<note place="margin">Abraham. Philo.</note> He reduced all the effects of the ſecond cauſes to the firſt cauſe immediatlie: he dyd not attribute to the ſunne, the light of the day: nor to cloudes the rain<hi>:</hi> nor to eyes the ſight: nor to eares the hearing: nor to other next inſtruments of ſenſe the cauſe of their facultie, not to the feet force to goe: not brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the lunges: not concoction to the ſtomak<hi>:</hi> not to trees and ſeeds their yerelie fruits: but he reduced all things immediatlie to him onlie which ſpreadeth abroad his benignitie, and beneuolence largelie, frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and freelie in all places: he bendeth all his forces to hym alone, hoping by hym only to be ayded: and ſtaying him ſelf vpon him only: neither truſting vpon heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor vpon earth, ayer, beaſts, plants or rootes, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to loue them as cauſes. And (as a man may ſay) he trauerſed through all the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and troupes of the hoſt of all ſecond and inſtrumental cauſes apperteining to the <hi>OEconomie</hi> or general diſpoſition of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal nature, for to approche vnto the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign head: the Creator of ſubſtances: the giuer of formes: the firſt mouer: firſt cauſe, and cauſe of cauſes: to the ende to loue him only, and to giue him only thankes for all benefits receiued. And this Philoſophie of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5177:19"/> Abraham was as a ſhining beam of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie of nature before ſinne: which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie conſiſted in cleaning wholie to God, and depending vpon God in all things: not reſting vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſelfe, nor vpon any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: whereupon alſo God loued him more, and was more reuealed to hym, than to tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe that loue the ſecond cauſes, and ſearch deeplie in to them, not ſatisfied otherwiſe with the firſt. In like maner in matters of faith, thoſe which doe reſt altogether vpon the Church ſhal rather be illuminated of the holy Ghoſt, than thoſe which doe not giue credit to her, but vpon a caution or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ſome natural reaſon. If any would know the way how to render a reaſon of his faith, and of all obſeruances of the Church <hi>S. Peter</hi> thereunto doeth exhort him. And in <note place="margin">1.
<hi>Petr.</hi> 3.</note> dede the ſtudie of ſuch a ſcience is the moſt noble and moſt worthie that is in the world: only let him be humble, and holde this for a principle or maxime: though he vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not the reaſon of any obſeruances: yet notwithſtanding the ſame is grounded vpon ſome iuſt reaſon aboue his capacitie. And when he hath layed for his ground this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, and comyng afterward to ſearche the motiues and reaſons of the Churche: then the knowleige of the general diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5177:19"/> and gouernement of the Church ſhall teach him conſiderations more deep, more excellent, more ample, more confortable, and ſhall repleniſh his mynde with a cleerer light than the knowleige of al Naturs vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes: and therein he ſhal take more pleaſure, than if he had in his head the collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and gatherings of al the knowleige in the worlde faſt ſowed one to an other, and coulde gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a reaſon of the whole diſpoſition of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural things in al parts of the whole frame of this worlde.</p>
            <p>In the primatiue Church, <hi>Sineſius</hi> the great <note place="margin">Sineſius.</note> philoſopher called by Chriſtians to the ſtate if a Biſhop, vvould not accept the ſame, but with reſeruation of ſome opinions of the ethnical philoſophie. The fathers condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his deſire, aſſuring them ſelues, that ſo excellent a wit would eaſilie caſt of al thoſe reſeruations of his philoſophical folie, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with wiſe and learned men of the Church. And in dede this learned man being made Biſhop, did ſoone caſt away al reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations of his ſeueral opinions<hi>:</hi> and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him ſelfe in al points to the Church, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning him ſelfe, and deriding his own va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, proceding rather from the root of folie and pryde of a philoſopher, than of malice. And truelie to addict him ſelfe obſtinatlie to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5177:20"/> ſome particularities of opinions againſt the vniuerſalitie,
<q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 27.</note>it is the part of one that is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the firſt elements and principles of Chriſtianitie: and a token of a ſhort and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iudgemen,</q> that hath a verie ſhmal beam of brightnes, and is ſo poore of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, as he is not hable to conceiue that the riuer which he dwelleth next vnto, is much leſſe than the Ocean ſea: and that the ſterres be much greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they appear to his eyes: eſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming the greateſt things that he knoweth to be the moſt that God can doe in that kynde: and conſidereth but one thing onlie, where he ought to conſider an hundred thouſand, perſuading him ſelfe euermore to haue in the compaſſe of his brain, all that God is hable to doe, or wil doe, meſuring all things by his own capacitie, and ſufficiencie: which is not onlie an extreme folie, but alſo verie daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. for ſuch folk vpon the leaſt motion of the deuil wil throw them ſelues from the high pinacle of the temple down to the ground: I mean from the firmament of the Church, to the bottomles pit of hereſie. Wil we then be aſſured neuer to erre, and to haue our ſpirite quiets, peacible amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g all the wherl wyndes and tempeſts of hereſies? this is the onlie mean: he that walketh in the ſpirit of the Church, is in the high way: he goeth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5177:20"/> not in darknes: he goeth by day, and ſetteh ſure footing. The church is to him a bulwark of quietneſſe: a wall of braſſe: a ſtay more ſure then the firmament of heauen: yea, I ſay truelie, more ſure than the firmament of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. For rather the heauen ſhal fall in pieces, and all the whole frame of the worlde ſhal fall into co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion, and nature ſhal erre, rather than the Church ſhal come to errour in that doctrine of the ſaluation, which ſhe doeth teach her children. And good reaſon: for her vnderſtanding his higher than the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of all nature: for it is the vncreated vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, the holie Ghoſt, God him ſelf, which doth gouerne the ſame immediatlie. And for the Churches ſake, heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, earth, and all Nature haue bene made, and doe conſiſt: without whoſe prayers, the fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of the whole worlde could not ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d one moment. The Angels them ſelues (as S. Paul ſayth) are all <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10</note> to miniſter to them which receiue the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of ſaluation, which are the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the church.</p>
            <p>But I will no forther open the priuileiges of Grace, the heauenlie and liuelie comforts which the children of the catholike Church haue. The catholike Church is the onlie fortreſſe impregnable; the wiſeman to her wil haue his recourſe, and ſhal be ſaued.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:5177:21"/> She is the ſtrong fort of the citie of God, founded vpon the rock, whiche can not be vndermined:
<q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 27.</note> fortified by the inuincible for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the holie Ghoſt, garded by heauenlie armies, vvhich are camped round about, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed of all ſides with the fauour of the almightie.</q> She is the true earthlie Paradiſe, where the tree of lyfe is planted, which all of her houſe may freelie vſe, and thereby receiue nouriſhment of lyfe euerlaſting. She is the true houſe of God, where he doth diſpoſe his graces, and all his goodes and the ſouue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign felicitie. And who euer can taiſt of the fruit of the name
<hi>Catholike:</hi> he ſhal fynde hem ſelfe happie, and ſhal perceiue in that he is a Catholike, he is as it were weeded out of him ſelfe to be tranſplanted in God: and being loſtin him ſelfe, he ſhal fynde him ſelfe grafted, and rooted in God, in whom he ſhal ſtand more ſurelie, more liuelie, more happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and be more his own man, thau ſtanding in him ſelfe: where vpon his ſoule ſhal be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with true, ſound, parfite, ſoueraign, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, and euerlaſting ioye.</p>
            <p>I doe not call in queſtion whether the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Churche be viſible, nor where ſhe is being a ſocietie, not of Angels, or of ſoules ſeparated from the bodie, but of men. She muſt neceſſarilie be viſible, that one may ſay,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5177:21"/> there is the Church, pointing to her with the fingar, and ſhewing her to the eye: otherwyſe (ſayth S. Auguſt.)
<q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. tract.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. <hi>in</hi> 10.</note>no man could be aſſured of the vnitie, in the which men muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilie enter, and holde them ſelfes, to the ende they may be ioyned to the head &amp; communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with all the other members thereof. And our lord ſhould in vain haue bidden men reſort to the Church, and obey it, if it were inuiſible to the face of the whole worlde, ſo that ſhe can not by any manner of wayes be hidden, nor darckned in the earth, no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re than the ſonne in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</q> Yea (ſayth S Iohn Chriſoſtom)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Chryſ. ho.</hi> 4. <hi>in cap.</hi> 6.
<hi>Efa.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>it were more eaſie to put out the light of the ſonne, than to darcken the Church.</hi> And thoſe which ſay that the Church which was planted of the Apoſtles, and dyd lighten the Gentiles, is no more extant, and that ſhe is loſt many a day agoe; and that ſtrayght after the Apſtoles ſhe was eclipſed of her light, and became an Apoſtata, in ſuch ſort as the worlde is entered in to darknes as before: and thoſe which doe compare her to the Sinago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue in the time of Eli: thoſe (I ſay) are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie impudent, and their impudencie can not be heard with out indignation, for that it is contumeliouſe to the ſonne of God: as if the ſonne of God (which ſayd, that he is the light of the world, and that he came to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5177:22"/> all, to deſtroye the vvorkes of the deuil, and to diſpoſſeſſe him of his raign) had not doen that vvhich he promiſed, nor that vvhich he came for: and as yf his light had bene as a flaſh of lightening vaniſhing avvay, and not as a ſonne riſing, to chaſe out effectuallie the darknes of the vvorld. This is a mooſt vile and ſhamefull abaſing of Chriſts honour and eſtimation: this is to take from him the deſerued inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of all Nations, vvhich GOD the <hi>father</hi> promiſed vnto him: this is (as it vvere) to ſpoyle him of his dignitie and the royal ſcepter, and to plucke him downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his throne, and to take from him his roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Diadem, vvhich the <hi>father</hi> gaue him, and to make, that GOD hath not kept his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe. They vvhich vſe thies vvoordes are not in the Church them ſelues ſayth S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin.
<q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. in pſalm.</hi> 101.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſayeſt: that the Church is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, becauſe thou art not in her.</hi> Look vvell to the matter: thou art not in dede in her: but ſhe is and ſhal be extant, though thou art not.</q> Al that the ſcripture doth teach <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numer.</hi> 20. 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8. <hi>Math.</hi> 18.
<hi>Acto.</hi> 15. 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.</note> feighteth againſt this impudent ſaying. It hath bene foretold that the glorie of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cound houſe of GOD ſhal be greater then the glory of the firſt: that ſhe ſhal reach
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5177:22"/> from one ſea to an other: from the Orient <note place="margin">1,
<hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.
<hi>Eſa,</hi> 2, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. <hi>Mich.</hi> 4. <hi>Math.</hi> 7.</note> to the Occident: that ſhe ſhal fill Aſia, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica, Grece, Italy, all tounges, all nations, and the Iles ferre of: and that the ſauiour ſhal make as it vvere nevv heauens, and nevv earth: ſo that the Sinagogue in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the Church is no more then one ſtarre in compariſon of the Sonne, and had but fevv litle ſpartles of that light whre of the full brightnes is ſpred vpon the Church. <hi>Origin ſayth,</hi> that the firſt ſigne <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi>
6.</note> giuen to Gedeon of the flyſe only devved from heauen, the earth round about re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining all drye, did prefigure the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue: and the ſecound ſigne of all the earth bedevved, the flyſe contynevving drie did prefigurat the Churche. <hi>In Daniel</hi> alſo, the Church vvas prefigured by the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.</note> litle ſtone cut from the mountaine vvithout hand of man, the vvhich hauing broken the Image of Gold, of Syluer, of braſſe, of Iron, and of clay, vvhich did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the Empires of the vvorld, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a great mountaine, and did fill the vvhole earth, vvhere vpon ſanct Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin doth argue againſt the heretikes:
<q>If the Ievyes be ſayd to be blinde for not hauing ſeene the ſtone being but litle,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5177:23"/> what blindnes is that in them which can not ſee the ſame being a mountaine? ſo thoſe (ſaith he) which denie the Church diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed throwgh the world, doe not ſtumble againſt de litle ſtone but againſt the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</q> 
               <hi>Eſaie</hi> expreſſely fortold, that the Church <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 2. 54. 66.</note> ſhal be as a mountaine manifeſtly, lifted vp aboue the mountaines whervnto all nations
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.</note> ſhall reſort:
<q>vvhich <hi>our Sauiour</hi> him ſelfe confirmed, ſaying that his Church is a citie ſet on a montaine which can not be hidden, what ſhal I ſay more</q> 
               <hi>(ſayth S. Auguſtin)?</hi>
               <q>the Churche, is ſhee not manifeſt? doe not we ſhew it with our fingar? and thoſe that doe not ſee ſo great a mountaine, be they not blinde which againſt the ſhining candle, put in a candelſticke do ſhut theyr eyes?</q> 
               <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> writeth elega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly hereof againſt the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes of his time:
<q>the ſtone cutt without the hand is becomme the mountaine filling the vvorlde; and thincke you (ſaith he) that it is within your dennes? this is to calu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>niat al the vniuerſal vvorld.</q> Thou maieſt eaſily ſee the citie ſett vpon a mountaine, the Church ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique which can not be hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Moreouer <hi>S. Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, that by Gods prouidence, it
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. in pſal.</hi> 101.</note> hath bene ſo diſpoſed, that the teſtimonies of Ieſus Chriſt are obſcure in the olde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, but thoſe of the church are manifeſt, to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5177:23"/> the end that men ſhould haue recourſe to the Church for cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeil, to learne of hir their ſaluation. And he ſaith forther that the Church ſithens the Apoſtles time hath not only not loſt any part of her light, but alſo hath alwayes augmented the ſame, ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and encreaſyng, as the new moone from ſmal light to a greater. If any one (ſaith he) doe not perceiue the moone in the firſt point of hir increaſing, one might excuſe the vveakenes of his eyes: but he that doth not perceiue the ſame in her fulnes, that man is ſtarke blinde. From the tyme of the Apoſtles, vvhen the Church did not ſhew as yet very much hir face vpon the arth, ſimple men we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re deceiued by falſe teachers, ſaying, here is the Church, here is Chriſt, vvounding (as it vvere in the dark of the moon) ſimple and plain meaning folke: but now how blinde is he that erreth in the ful moone? <hi>Pope Leo</hi> the
<note place="margin">S. Leo.</note> firſt, <hi>S. Hilaire,</hi> and other auncients, vvhich liued in the mayn courſe of mightie hereſies <note place="margin">S. Hilarie.</note> doe vvitnes, that the Church vvas neuer darkenid ſithens the Apoſtles, by the infectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hereſies. The Church (ſay they) may be diminiſhed in the Globe of multitude of chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, but not in light and clearnes: much leſſe by the perſecutions of tyrannes: for (as ſayeth <hi>Tertullian) the bloud of Chriſtians is the</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:5177:24"/> 
               <hi>ſeed of the Church, and euerie martyr is as the grayne of wheate falling on the earthe,</hi> which bringeth foorth manye. Poore Cicero <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic. l.</hi>
2. <hi>q. Ac.</hi>
               </note> ſearching the ſoueraigne God, complaineth, ſaying, by the diſſention of philoſophers vve are conſtrained to be ignorant of our Lord, and can not know vvhich is he that vve ought to worſhip for Lord and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerner of the world. This can not beſayd of the Church; the contradictions which heretikes doe make againſt her, doe not darken her, but make her rather better knowne. and <hi>(as Vincentius Lyrinenſis</hi> ſayth) <note place="margin">Vinc. Lyr.</note> doe ſcoure her and make her brighter, geuing occaſion to catholikes to vnderſtand cleerlie and feruentlie that vvhich before they beleued couertly and coldly. And it is certei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the Church had more knowleige of God, in ſome certein articles in the tyme of S. Auguſtin, then in other tymes before; and in the tyme of S. Bernard, then in the tyme of S. Auguſtin: and at this day more then ſhe had ſince the tyme of the Apoſtles: ſo that ther is now none that ſeeth not cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the light of the Church, except thoſe vvhoſe eyes ſatan hath put out, and vvhich are willingly blynde: ſith all now doe know vvhere is the cheire of S. Peter, the Church Catholike, Apoſtolique and Romain; which
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5177:24"/> hath the name of Catholike, the ſucceſſion of Biſhoppes ſithens S. Peter to this day; the conſent of people, and nations, and many other wel knowen markes, whiche do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingwiſhe the ſame from all falſe religion, of panims, of Iewes, and of heretikes, and doth make it ſufficiently euident, that none can be excuſed, neither thoſe which refuſe to ioyne vnto her, nor thoſe that do depart from her. I wil not here ſett downe all the markes of the true Church, as if this preſent treatice were to that end, but I ſhal touche only ſome few.</p>
            <div type="proofs">
               <head>TWELVE MARCKES OF <hi>the true Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt marke of the true Church is the name <hi>Catholike,</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all heretikes would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be theirs, yet neuer could they obthain thus much,
<hi>(ſayth</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtin)</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. Auguſt. lib. cont. epi. fund. c.</hi> 4.</note> that if a Panime demaunded of an heretike the place where the Catholikes doe aſſemble them ſelues, he durſt not ſhew his owne Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue. And <hi>S. Ciril</hi> ſayth, if thou goeſt in a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyril. cat.</hi> 18.</note> citie, doe not aſke vvhere is the Church, nor where the houſe of GOD is: for the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes ſay that they haue the Church, and the howſe of god: but aſke where is the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5177:25"/> Catholike Church, for that name Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like is proper to the holy Church, mother of vs all, that are of right beleif: and an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retyke vvould be mocked and laughed at to ſhew his Churche for the catholike. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cianus</hi> hath treated of this point expreſſely where he ſaith: <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is my name, <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> is my ſurname: that doeth name me, this maketh me knowne: the name catholike is not deriued of any one man: it doth not ſound any thing of an heretike: it is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to any particullar Authour; it agreeth to the principal head &amp; body of that tree, vvhoſe braunches beinge cutt of, are the ſectes of heretikes: but the tree it ſelfe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, mainteined by his roote: and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth alwaye the ſame, vvhich is all one whole body, and called <hi>Catholike:</hi> but euerie here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie taketh the name of ſome one which is the authour therof: where vpon <hi>S. Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>than. ſerm.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>nt. Arria.</note> againſt the Arrians ſayth: <hi>Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple neuer tooke their names of their Biſhoppe: no, we are chriſtians, and ſo named, not of the Apoſtles them ſelues,</hi> but of our lord <hi>in whome we haue beleued by the voice of Biſhoppes and Apoſtles, Thoſe which haue taken their faith of others are by good right ſurnamed from the cheefe of their hereſie. Lactantius</hi> ſayth, <hi>the only Catholike</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ct. li.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Church is that which keepeth the true worſhippe;</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:5177:25"/> 
                  <hi>of God: this is the fountein of trueth, the houſe of faith, the temple of God: in whom if any do not enter, or from whom if any doth depart, he cutteth him ſelf of from hope of lyfe, and of euerlaſting ſaluation: but euerie ſect of heretikes doth pretend that the catholike Church is on ther ſyde: how be it bearing the names of Marcionites or Arrians, they are no more Chriſtians; they haue loſt their name chriſtian in taking ſtraunge names of men.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Iuſtine the martyr:</hi> S. Ireneus S. Iohn <note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. Chryſ. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 33 <hi>in act. Apoſt. Iuſt. mar. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triph. S. Ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n. lib.</hi> 1.
<hi>ca.</hi> 20.</note> Chriſoſtome, <hi>The ſectes</hi> (ſay they) <hi>be called of the name of the arche heretike, but to vs, no man hath giuen a name: faithe it ſelf which is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike ſurnameth vs ſo:</hi> and S. Ierome; <hi>If thou</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">S. Hieron. cont. Luciferanos.</note> 
                  <hi>heare thoſe which are called Chriſtians, to beare a name: not of our lord Ieſus Chriſt, but of ſome other, (as Marcionites, Valentinians) know ye certenly that they are not the Church of Ieſus Christ, but a Sinagoge of Antichriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now yow poore abuſed Lutherans and Caluiniſts, be holde the horroure of your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thomleſſe pitt; you are no more Chriſtians; and you haue no part in the ſaluation by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. All aucient Fathers do witneſſe with one conſent, that the only
<hi>Catholike</hi> is in the Church of Ieſus Chriſt; and all that bear the name of one particular man be he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, and excluded from the kyngdome of Ieſus Chriſt. Thoſe witneſſes can not be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5177:26"/> reproued: and this is one marueilous iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God againſt heretikes, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for the Catholikes: by the Creed of the Apoſtles, it is a neceſſarie conſequens, that any Church (if it be a true) muſt needes be catholike: but there is not a ſociete in the vvorld, which doth poſſeſſe the name <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,</hi> ſaue only the Romain Church. All o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will call them ſelues, <hi>Arrians, Lutherans, Caluiniſts,</hi> the
<hi>reformed Church, Goſpellers, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,</hi> and ſuch other kinds of ſpecial names as they haue: but Catholikes doe not ſo, for in all parts of the vvorld (vvhere the name Catholike Church doth ſounde) it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and vnderſtood, to be the <hi>Romain</hi> Churche, yea by the heretikes them ſelues. A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that paſſeth by <hi>Geneua</hi> being aſked what he is, if he anſwere, I am a Catholik, is taken of no man there for a
<hi>Caluiniſt.</hi> Seek not here to blynde your ſelues againſt ſo manifeſt a trueh: but forſake both the ſect, and alſo the name of theſe wicked deceiuers, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheheretikes of this tyme, which will draw you with them ſelues in to their, bottomleſſe pitt of euerlaſting damnation, if you do not enter again in to the Church and mount vp in to the firmament of Catholikes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecound marke of the true Church is the <hi>ſucceſsion of Biſhoppes</hi> ſithens S. Peter,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5177:26"/> to this day, which neuer hath bene interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; the vvhich ſucceſſion the fathers haue alwayes obiected againſt heretikes of their tyme as an inuincible argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for euen as to the propagation of mankinde, mariage is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie: ſo to the procreation of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God according to the ſpirit, the order of preiſthood is inſtituted, vvhich can not be continewed perpetuallie, but by ſpiritual propagation from thoſe prieſts whom Ieſus Chriſt did firſt inſtitute. It is not ſo of kings, as it is of preiſtes, for if all the kings of the earth ſhould faile at once: the people might create new. But if all the prieſts of the world ſhould happen to fayle: it is not in the power of all mankinde to make new. Their inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is diuine, and not humain. Ieſus Chriſt him ſelfe muſt come again in perſon in to this vvorld for to inſtitute ſom new. <hi>S. Ireneus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iran. li.</hi> 3, <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> ſayth, that by this ſucceſſion all heretikes be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded: for neuer heretike could ſhew his next predeceſſor in communion of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin. And to proue that the Romain Church is the true Church, he rekeneth the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of Rome from <hi>S. Peter,</hi> vnto <hi>S. Eluther</hi> the Pope of his tyme, vvhich vvas the twelveth. <hi>Tertullianus, Euſebius, Proſper, S. Hieronimus, S. Auguſtin, Epiphanius, Optatus,</hi> and all the auncient fathers haue vſed this argument
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:5177:27"/> againſt heretikes. <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayth, ſhew the
<note place="margin">Tertul. lib. de praeſcr.</note> begin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing of your churches, and the orderlie ſucceſſion of your Biſhoppes deriued by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome one of the Apoſtles, as vve doe ſhew the orderlie ſucceſſion in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Church, from <hi>S. Peter.</hi> Account (ſayeth <note place="margin">8. <hi>Aug. epiſt.</hi> 165. <hi>in pſal.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Auguſtin)</hi> the prieſts ſithens the ſtate of S. Peter: and look in to that order of fathers vvhich haue ſucceded one an other: and you ſhal fynde that the Romain Church is the ſame ſtone, that the proud gates of hell can not vanquiſh. And he ſayth further, that the <note place="margin">Aug. cont. ep. fundam.</note> ſucceſſion of prieſts in the romain Church by one continual line holdeth him in that Church. Likerwiſe,
<hi>Optatus, Shew</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>the first beginning of your chayer, you which wil</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Optatus lib,</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>chalenge the holy Church vnto your ſelues.</hi> And <hi>Epiphanius</hi> hauing orderlie recited the names of all the Biſhops from S. <hi>Peter,</hi> vnto <hi>Siri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius then Biſhop,</hi> which was the thirtie eight,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiph. har.</hi> 27.</note> he addeth: <hi>Let no man meruail if we be ſo exact in this recital, for by thies things the euident trueth of the Church doth alvvayes ſhevv it ſelf.</hi> If then thoſe auncient fathers haue ſo greatlie eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that continuation of twelue, twentie, or forty ſouerain biſhops, ſucceſſors of S. <hi>Peter:</hi> how much ſtronger is that argument at this day for vs which ſhew the continuacion of more than two hundred thirtie thre, without
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5177:27"/> exception. This argument is inſoluble: and all the heretikes of the worlde ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not anſwer the ſame, for the Church can not be without prieſts, nor without Biſhops and paſtors. There muſt needes be (as S. Paul ſayth) ſome for the edefying of the body of Ieſus Chriſt, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.</note> vntil he come to iudge the worlde. And (as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> ſayth) the Church which is without prieſts is not a Church: and none <note place="margin">S. Hierom.</note> can be prieſt, if he be not ordeined by a Biſchop, being ſucceſſor of the apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like prieſthode. This marke is not only moſt certain, &amp; moſt euident, but forcible to know <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Con. Laud. con;</hi> 12,
<hi>do.</hi> 61. <hi>c.</hi>
                  </note> the true Church. for where the ſucceſſion of prieſthode is, there is the ſucceſſion of doctrine: <hi>Moyſes,</hi> the <hi>prophets,</hi> our
<hi>ſauiour</hi> him ſelfe in the Goſpel doth affirme the ſame. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. <hi>Math.</hi> 2.</note> Now then, we ſhew the ſucceſſion of prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode of the ſoueraign Biſhop of this tyme, by aſcending fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> predeceſſor to predeceſſor vpward, vntil we arriue at <hi>S. Peter,</hi> and enter as it were in to the ſide of Ieſus. Your <hi>Caluin</hi> ſeing him ſelfe by this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo intangled
<note place="margin">Caluin.</note> that he could not ſlip away, he ſtriueth, he wringeth him ſelfe, he tourneth and toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, he broyleth with ſo great rage, as he ſpeweth out a whole flud of iniures againſt Popes, prieſts, and Biſhops. Oh the madde dogge, ſeing cleerlie that ſucceſſion is a verie
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:5177:28"/> certein ſigne of the true Church, to which he could not anſwer, whereby he is proued to be a deceiuer ſent of the deuil: he caſteth from the poyſonful pit of his harte, iniureis ſufficient to darken the heauen. O ye Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, and Caluiniſts, if you be capable of reaſon; if you may be taught by the holie Ghoſt, if you be touched with the deſire of your ſaluation: then examin you without paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this argument: hearken to that which your own conſciences ſhal teache you, and be ye not enemies to your own ſaluation. For ſithins that you haue not the order of prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood from any Biſhop, ſucceſſor to the Apoſtles: you are owt of the communion of the Church of IESVS Chriſt; you be without Church, without prieſthood, and without any mediation towards God: for that you haue not any preiſt of the order of the <hi>Mediator.</hi> Your miniſters be thoſe that <hi>S. Ciprian</hi> ſpeaketh of, who without lawful <note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. Ciprian lib.</hi> 4. <hi>ep.</hi> 9.</note> calling, without gods ordinance, without eccleſiaſtical <hi>order,</hi> doe appoint them ſelues to be head ouer raſh men, take to them ſelfs titles of Biſhops: and like apes, they reſemble mens actions; and them ſelues being not in in the Church counterfait the face of the Church; arrogating to them ſelues her au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, &amp; truth; bleſſing others, being them
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:5177:28"/> ſelues curſed of God: promiſing life, being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues dead: calling vpon God, being blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers: adminiſtring prieſthood, being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues prophane: preſenting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to the altar as interceſſors to God, being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues ſacrilegiouſe, &amp; prouokers of gods wrath: their preaching is not preaching, but preua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rication of the woord of God: their prieſthood is not prieſthood, but a ſeruice of the deuil, and miniſterie of Antichriſte. for Apes be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes Apes, and neuer ſhal be men: and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes alwayes heretikes, how ſo euer they doe counterfait, and neuer ſhal be Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, except they enter again in to the boſom of the Church, where the lauful ſucceſſion of prieſthood of the Apoſtles doth remain.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third marke is <hi>Antiquitie:</hi> for euen as the good ſeed was ſowen in the field by the houſe houlder, before the cockle by the enemie: ſo it is certein, that the true church is more aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient than the falſe. Now, that the catholike, Apoſtolike, and Romain Church is the ſame that IESVS Chriſt him ſelfe hath inſtituted, &amp; more auncient then all the ſects of hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wil forſe them to confeſſe.</p>
               <p>In all notable chaunges of religion ſix things are to be marked: the <hi>Author:</hi> the
<hi>new opinion:</hi> the <hi>tyme when it began:</hi> the <hi>place where it began:</hi> the
<hi>Impugners that it had:</hi> the <hi>ſmall</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:5177:29"/> 
                  <hi>number of folowers when</hi> the ſame began to make her ſeparation of communion from the religion that it dyd forſake. firſt, vve know that the Author of the hereſie of <hi>Arria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> was a preiſt of Alexandria named <hi>Arrius:</hi> of
<hi>Neſtorians</hi> a Biſhop of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople named <hi>Neſtorius:</hi> of
<hi>Lutherans</hi> a monk of the order of S. Auguſtin named <hi>Luther.</hi> Secondlie we know that the new doctrine of <hi>Arrius</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, that the ſunne of God was a creature: Of
<hi>Neſtorius,</hi> that there was two perſonnes in Ieſus Chriſt: Of <hi>Luther,</hi> that the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is not a ſacrifice, and that man is Iuſtified by that onely ſpecial faith which he hath of his own iuſtification. Thirdlie we know that the ſect of Arrius dyd beginne the yere of our Lord 324. that of Neſtorius, the yere of 431. that of Luther, the yere
1517. Fowertlie we know that the Arrianiſme dyd beginne in Aegipte: the hereſie of Neſtorius in Thrace: that of Luther in Saxonie. Fiftlie we know that the Arrians were Impugned by <hi>Pope Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſter,</hi> by the <hi>Councel of Nice,</hi> by <hi>S. Athanaſius'</hi> by <hi>S. Hilarie,</hi> and many others: the Neſtorians by <hi>Pope Celeſtin,</hi> by the <hi>Councel of Epheſus,</hi> by S. Ciril, and many others: the Lutherans by <hi>Pope Leo the tenth:</hi> by the
<hi>Councel of Trent,</hi> by all vniuerſities catholikes, and by many Doctors. Finally, vve know that in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5177:29"/> when all thoſe archeheretikes did ſeparate them ſelues from the communion of catholikes, they were ſmall in number, an that euen then the catholikes were diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed throughout the world in infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. None of all thoſe thinges can be obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Lutherans and Caluiniſts againſte the catholikes. Firſt they haue neuer obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs, the autor of our faith contrary to theirs: neither haue they named vs after any particular man, vvhich they wolde verie willinglie haue done if they could. Secondly they doe not ſhew the beginninge of any our nevv doctrine, if they aſcend not vp to the Apoſtles vvhoſe nouelty is ours, and is our antiquitie againſt all hereſies. They are not alſo hable to ſhew any tyme certain of our faling from the Church: nor the place, neither where it ſhould haue begun; nor thoſe which did impugne the ſame, as new: nor that any councels haue bene celebrated againſt her: nor finally that this our Church catholike, Apoſtolike, and Romain, did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate it ſelf from ſome greater, that was before, in ſuch ſorte as thoſe which did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with the Romaine Church vvere fewe in member, and that the reſt of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were farre more greater. For it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the epiſtles of <hi>S. Gregorie,</hi> the Pope
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:5177:30"/> vvhich he did vvrite to the Biſhops of the Eaſt, of <hi>Afrike,</hi> of
<hi>Spaine,</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> of <hi>Italie,</hi> that almoſte all the Chriſtians of the world did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with him. Now it is a thovvſand yeeres paſt ſithens S. Greg: and the doctrine of faith vvhich he did teache, is the ſame that the Church doth teach at this day.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fowerth marke is <hi>continewance</hi> without being interrupted. It is foretould in <hi>Daniel,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.</note> that the raigne of the church ſhall neuer be diſperſed: and in <hi>ſanct Paule,</hi> that hereſies
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim,</hi> 3.</note> can not long ſtand: the Churche being like the brightnes of the firmament vvhich ſhineth in perpetual eternitie: Hereſie is as a Comet conceiued of the vapours of the earth, vvhereof the flame ceaſeth ſo ſone as his earthly noriſhement doth faile. The Church in an other ſorte is as a continual flud which can not drye. Hereſie is as a flud of tempeſt vvhich preſently doth faile: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſayth: Be not you (ſayth he) amaſed to ſee the fluds ſwellinge and roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In illud pſa.</hi> 97 <hi>Ad nihilum d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ent tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam aqua de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urrens.</hi>
                  </note> for a tyme. It is a violence of vvater vvhich runneth downe, and ſhall ceaſe verie ſone: for the ſame can not long continue. many hereſies be alredie dead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they haue runne in theyr channel as long as they could; they be ſlydden away: the rootes be drie: and hardlie ſhal one finde the marcke where
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:5177:30"/> they were. It is verie certein that the Church catholike, Apoſtolike and Romain hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continued ſince the Apoſtles in her viſible brightnes vnto this day: vvhich thing if heretikes doe not fullie grant, yet doe they confeſſe that thoſe things which they blame in the ſame, vvere alredie brought in before a thowſand, or twelue hundred yeres. But vvhat hereſie hath euer laſted any thing near that tyme? yet I vvil confound them by this argument: Before that Luther did ſtart vp, beſydes the Romaine Church, there was not in the vvorld but thes religions, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme, Iudaiſme, Machometiſme,</hi> and the relikes of
<hi>Neſtorianiſme</hi> in Grece. But it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein by the confeſſion of Lutherans and Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſts them ſelues, that the Church of IESVS Chriſte was not in any one of thies ſectes; vvhereof it foloweth that ſhe was in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Church, or els quyte extinguiſed in al the vvhorld, vvhich can not be. Trulie this marke of the true church is famous: for ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
<hi>Theobutes</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> the firſt Archeheretikes vntil Luther, two hundred diuers hereſies haue had their courſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome were vpholden by verie mightie Patrones: by Emperours, by kynges, by lerned men, making innumerable books, out of the vvhich a man vvoulde haue ſayed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:5177:31"/> that they could neuer be blotted. And notwithſtanding, by the wonderfull prouidence of God thei be ſo weeded out of the earth, that there remaineth nothing at all, nether of the followers, nor of their bookes, nor of theyr doctrine, nor any ſigne at all, but that which is found in the bookes of catholikes; who if they had not written their names in their books, vve had not knovven that ſuch hereſies had euer bene in the vvorld: and there is no doute but the flouds of hereſies of theis tymes vvil alſo ſlyde avvay ſhortly.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fyueth marke of the true Church is the <hi>largenes of the raigne.</hi> And this marke is verie euident in the Catholike Church, the which doth fructifie throughout the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal vvorld in both the hemiſpheres; And the ſunne doth not ſtreache his beames fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſhe. I know vvel that ſhe hath not the temporal regiment of external Iuſtice throughout the whole vvorld: but ſhe hath euerie where obedient childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So that there is no tonge, nor people, nor climat of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie inhabited, vvhere (if perhaps the moſt parte be not carholikes) yet at the leaſte there are ſome. I ſay ſome notable number; which aſſamble them ſelues in the Church and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate Catholiklie in the Sacraments of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:5177:31"/> the Church: among the <hi>Turkes,</hi> among the <hi>Perſians,</hi> among the <hi>Tartarians,</hi> among the <hi>Panymes,</hi> throughout the compaſſe of the earth: for the carholike Church is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreined vvithin the bonds of <hi>Italie, Fraunce, Spaine, Germanie, England, Polland, Rome, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie, Greece, Siria, Armenia, Ethiope, Egipt,</hi> and other countries vvherof the names are vvel knovvn vnto vs, and where the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes be in infinite number: but ſhe doth ſpread her ſelf in to the new world, and in all thoſe foure partes of that nevv vvorld, vvhere ſhe hath many Churches, without mingling of hereſies: of the Eaſt ſyde in the <hi>Indians:</hi> of the weſt ſyde in <hi>America:</hi> towardes the north in Iapon, towards the ſouth in <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilia:</hi> what hereſie is that, that euer had ſuch largenes? As for the ſectes of Lutherans and Caluiniſts, they haue not paſſed in Aſia, nor into Africa, nor in to Grece, nor into many prouinces of Europe. Yea euen in the verie ſprings of miſchief in the North, where he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies haue moſt might, there are not two townes neighbours poſſeſſed of one ſelf ſect. All hereſie is as a ſerpent. A ſerpent neuer <note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. Auguſt. lib. de paſto. ca.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp; lib. de vtil. credendi cap.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.</note> departeth farre of from his denne. And S. Auguſtine ſayth very wel that the Church is euery where, hereſie alſo euery where: But the Church is one and the ſelf ſame euery
<pb facs="tcp:5177:32"/> vvhere, where as hereſies be not the ſame euery where: but be of great diuerſitie, the one not knowinge the other. Wherof it doth appeare (ſayth he) that none of thoſe is the Catholike Church. And he compareth hereſies to boughes cut from the vine which abide in the place vvhere they fall vvithout fructifying: wher as the Church is the liuelie ſtocke, which doth bring fruit in all hir braunches throughout whereſo euer ſhe doth extend her ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The ſixt marke is the <hi>conqueſt of the world by efficacie of doctrine,</hi> which is the doctrine of the true Church, being liuelie, mightie, more pearſing then any two edged ſwoord and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerting effectuallie the ſoules to God. The Philoſophers (ſayth <hi>S. Athanaſius)</hi> with loftines of learning, and magnificence of ſpeche could neuer perſwade any one citie to take their laws of them, for that (ſayth he) their doctrine was dead and without force; and their ſpeche did not proceed of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, but of the ſpirit of man. Neither did any man euer read that the heretikes conuerted Idolators or Iewes to the faith. <hi>Their care</hi> (ſayth Tertullian) <hi>is not to conuert ſtraungers to Ieſus Chriſt, but to peruert hys do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticals,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tert. lib. de preſc. har.</note> 
                  <hi>and thoſe which he alredy gotten to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not to geue lyfe to the dead, but to giue deadlie poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:5177:32"/> 
                  <hi>to the liuing: not to lifte them vp which be on the grounde, but to make them fall that ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</hi> The efficacie of their doctrine is not to edifie; <hi>it ſerueth but to diſtroy,</hi> and this marke doth ſhew it ſelf very openlie in thies our dayes. Here is now the very large harveſt of the new world in ripenes. It behooueth to ſend workmen<hi>:</hi> but from whence doth the Lord of the harueſt take them? The Church catholike, and hereſie making both profeſſion to be of Ieſus Chriſt, their dueties are, to increaſe the howſehold of Ieſus Chriſt aſmuch as they can, by conuerting the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels to the faith. This notwithſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe IESVS CHRIST vvil not be planted in the hartes of ſtraungers by other handes then of his deare ſpouſe, therfore the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes only are they which preache the Goſpel to Idolators, and gaine them to Ieſus Chriſte. The heretikes haue neuer drawn the leaſt prouince from Paganiſme to Chriſtianitie. when we haue conuerted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Ieſus Chriſt: the heretikes come afterwardes to deceiue them. But men ſee that God doth not permit the worke of conuerting them, to any other then to his true Church: as we being thoſe
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Soc. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 27. <hi>Soz. l.</hi> 6. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 37. <hi>Theod. l.</hi> 4.</note> only which be the fiſhers of men; thoſe alone which draw the ſoules of men from the ſea of infidelitie, to the ſhoar of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:5177:33"/> The heretiks neuer throwe their net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in ſea, but after that we haue put the fiſh vpon the ſhoar, then they put all their gloire to rob and carie away ſome litle fiſhe, as the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues &amp; not as fiſhers. Euen ſo the <hi>Gothes</hi> being alredy made Catholike, demaunding Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Biſhops for to gouern their churches; <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> ſent them Arrians for to ſubuert them. The cauſe why the heretikes can not conuert the infidels to the faith is, for that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the ſcripture, they doe not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the true ſenſe vvhich is properlie the ſvvoard of the ſpirit. The vvordes of the ſcriptures are but as the ſheath which holdes the ſworde of the ſpirite. They then fighting, not vvith the ſworde, but vvith the ſheath onlye, it is no merueil if they doe not pearſe the hartes of Infideles. Beſydes that the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes and Idolaters belonge all to one ſelf maiſter: But in the Romain church, not onlie at the beginning, but euen at all tymes this efficacie hath bene found. This is the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Church vvhich did firſt conuert the Engliſhe men to the faith in the tyme of S. Gregorie the Pope: This is the Romain Church vvhich did conuert the Saxons and the vvhole coutrey of Almains, in the times of Pope Conon, and of Pope Zacharie: This is the ſelf ſame Church that conuerted the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:5177:33"/> 
                  <hi>Vandales, Bulgarians, Sclauonians, Polonians, Danes, Norwaies, Hungarians, Morauians,</hi> vvith infinite kinges &amp; people. And it is not paſt twoo hundred yeares ago ſyns rhat one only mounke <hi>S. Vincent</hi> of the order of S. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minike did conuert to the faith 25000. as vvel Iewes as ſararins. It is in our tyme that the new vvorlde receiued the faith of the Romaine Church. And it is not many yeres ago ſyns that ſome Turkes &amp; ſome Ievves vvere baptized at Rome and other places in the Romain Church. The Lutherans &amp; Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſts can not boaſte them ſelues to haue conuerted to their ſect neither Panimes nor Turkes, nor Iewes, vvhervpon it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that they be of the ſpirite of the deuil, ſithens that all their force is no maner of waye to get the Infidels, but only to diſtroy the Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſeuenth marke is the <hi>conformitie of doctrine with the Primitiue Church.</hi> Now that the auncient fathers did teach the ſame do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that we doe at this day, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for heretical that whiche we condemne, their bookes beare vvitnes therof; of the vvhich I wil ſay further, that who ſo euer readeth them ſhal neceſſarelie frame to him ſelf a catholike ſpirit, and ſhal neuer after drinke the venim of any hereſie. For all thies
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:5177:34"/> fathers, as they vvere well inſtructed vpon what ſtates the holy Ghoſt doth reſt him ſelf: ſo doe they breathe out nothing but humilitie, abatement of preſumption, abne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or denial of them ſelues, a ſoueraigne reuerence to the Church, a perpetual flame of charitie, and a care of ſpiritual vnitie, and as a man might ſaye, an indiuiſibilitie with the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The eight marke is <hi>holines of doctrine;</hi> (that is to ſaye) vvhen the profeſſion of doctrine doth not contein any falſehood concerning matter of faith; nor iniuſtice concerning maners: by the vvhich marke, it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted that there is no true Church in the vvorld but the catholike Church. For there is not a ſect in the vvorld be it of the
<hi>Panimes, Iewes, Turkes,</hi> or of heretikes as vvel olde as new, but it doth contein in her doctrine ſome manifeſt impietie, or ſome iniuſtice di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to reaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as the ſect of Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin doth make God authour of ſinne: and as much the cauſe of the treaſon of
<hi>Judas,</hi> as of the conuerſion of <hi>S. Peter:</hi> and doth teache that the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can not do any good worke. Beſyds that, al theyr writings be impugnours of chaſtitie, of virginitie, of Religion: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veihing againſt faſting, againſt vovves, againſt all orderlie deuotion in the church:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:5177:34"/> eſtabliſhing all vice: prouoking to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire: &amp; laboring to extingwiſhe the ſeed of immortalitie in the hartes of men. But the Church catholike is perfaictlie holie and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate in her doctrine: ſhe doth teach many things in her miſteries aboue reaſon, but nothing againſt reaſon: ſhe doth teache to auoide ſinne; ſhe doth correcte tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; ſhe doth comfort the penitentes: ſhe doth exhorte all her childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to walke holilie, iuſtlie, religiouſlie in all their wayes; and to haue their verie thoughts holie, purging, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminating, &amp; making them perfect for to preſent them holie to God. Come (ſayth S. <hi>Auguſtin)</hi> to our Churches; there is nothing ſet foorth to ſee, or to follow vvich is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; nothing vniuſt, nothing impure: there be inſinuated the comandementes of the true God, or his marueilles declared, or his giftes prayſed, or his graces demaunded. And ther is no perfect ioye nor true conſolation in the vvorlde but there: for that there is not any remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes in the world but there.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> The ninth marke is <hi>holines of lyfe,</hi> aſwel in prieſts as in the people. I know that this marke although many doe cauil at it, yet is it forceible: &amp; more notorius in catholikes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in all the ſectaries of the world. S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayth, <hi>that all the kindes of Iuſtice that the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:5177:35"/> 
                  <hi>of God haue in truth, the ſeruants of the deuil may haue the ſame in diſsimulation. The deuil</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>hath his meeke men, and his humble men: he hath his chaſte men, his almes giuers: his faſters, and all kinde of goodnes that god hath created for the ſaluation of men. The deuil hath brought in the ſame kind for to deceiue them: to the end that between the true good and the good faigned there ſhould be a confuſion, by the which the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not being eaſelie hable to diſcerne the true good from the good faigned,</hi> whiles they <hi>ſearching the men of God, they light vpon men of the deuil: and there is not any thing but onlie charitie, that the vncleane ſpirit can not counterfeit. All apparence of Iustice is found in deceiuers except onlie charitie, which is not found but in the onlie ſeruants of God: The holie Ghoſte hath reſerued to him ſelf onlie this vertue of charitie, in ſuch ſort, that by no other action of Iuſtice a man may ſo wel diſcerne where the holie ghost is, as by the vertue of charitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All hereſies at te beginninge come maſked with a ſuperficial holines, whiche for that it is not of the ſpirit of God, can not ſoundlie be there ſetled. And as the ape learned by arte to hold the candle after he hath ſtode ſome ſmall while in ſtead of a candelſtik, at the ſight of a nut caſte before him leaueth all for to runne after it: euen ſo they can not long time indure without manifeſting the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:5177:35"/> ſpirit wherof they be. And as theyr father was a morderer from the beginning, ſo they be come ſtraight waies theeues, kindlers of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi>
8.</note> diſcention, worſe then Panimes and Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, and aboue all other vices, Pride is to them peculiar. whereof S. Auguſtin ſayth: <hi>Inſundrie places there be ſundrie hereſies, but one</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Aug. l. de paſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>only mother pride hath ingendred them all, as alſo our onlie mother the Catholike Church hath brought foorth all faithfull Chriſtians diſperſed throughout the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And all thes hereſies doe ſpringe by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of ſome euil occaſion.
<hi>Egeſippus</hi> ſpeaking <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Egeſipp. apud Euſ. lib.</hi> 4.
<hi>hiſt. cap.</hi> 22.</note> of the firſt heretike, ſayth thus. <hi>then the church was called a virgin, not being yet corrupted by adulterous doctrine, but one Theobutes for that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Theobutes.</note> 
                  <hi>he was denied a biſhoprike; did beginne to trowble and corrupt all things.</hi> It apeareth in the eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 8.
<hi>Tert. con. Vale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Epiph. he</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.
<hi>Theod. l.</hi> 3. 5</note> hiſtorie that Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Magus, Valentin, Marrian, Arrius, and all thoſe olde monſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters did ſpring out from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe: for diſdeining that others were preferred before them, they made a ſecte for to reuenge them ſelues, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 16. <hi>I. Coch. in actis Luth.</hi> 15 17. <hi>Luth. in ep. ad Argen. l. con. Aug. &amp; l. de miſſa ſing.</hi>
                  </note> being eloquent and of great witt, and of thoſe that S. Iohn calleth falſe Prophetes iſſued out of the throat of the dragon: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane and deueliſh ſpirits, practiſing the kinges of the earth. <hi>Luther</hi> witneſſed his owne motiue in the firſt diſputation aginſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:5177:36"/> Ecchius, crying out, <hi>this cauſe is not begunne for the loue of God:</hi> Him ſelf hath written that willinglie he would haue denied the preſens of Ieſus Chriſt in the Euchariſt, if the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had not bene ſo cleare; for that therby (ſayth he) he did ſee that he might do much hart to the <hi>Papacie.</hi> He boaſteth him ſelf, that kinges, Princes, and Popes were not worthie to vntie the latche of his ſhoes: he ſayed that he would that they ſhould holde him for a holie man whether men would or no: that he did not eſteme muche a thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Ciprians,</hi> a thowſand <hi>Auguſtins:</hi> And for to ſhew more plainlie that his father is the king ouer all the children of pride, he ſayth, that the deuil did teache him that the maſſe was an euil thing, and that perſuaded by the <note place="margin">Conrae. Geſn. in Bibl. Luth.</note> reaſons of the deuil he did aboliſhe the maſſe. His owne followers them ſelues, haue deſcribed him to be a man full of a malitious ſpirit and without charitie, Eraſmus ſayth, that he was a manifeſt deceiuer; and that he
<note place="margin">Eraſ. ad vultu.</note> did neuer ſee one of thoſe which haue folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed him that did a mend them ſelues, but manye impaired. One of his owne miniſters whriteth in this maner, to the end that all the world may know that they be not Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, and that they do not truſt any vvhit at all in good vvorkes, they doe none at all: and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:5177:36"/> hauing chaunged the ſpirite of humilitie into arrogancie, &amp; redoubling their firſt diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions without faſting, without almes,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Luth. in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>up
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> call that kinde of life an euangelical
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Luther him ſelf hath acknowleged that his owne disciples gaue them ſelues to be more reuengeful, more couetous, proude, vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, vnrulie, and muche worſe then they had bene, then vvhen they vvhere Papiſts. Which thing the principal Lutherans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, and that their corruption vvas cheeflie cauſed for that they had taken away auriculer confeſſion, they vvhere deſirous to reſtore the ſame again by vvay of policie: &amp; for to conſtraine the people there to, they did preſent a requeſt to the Emperour Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the fifte, who refuſed to heare, them, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they would vnite them ſelues againe to the Church. His diſciples Caluin and Beza <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Soto in</hi> 4.
<hi>libr. ſent. vbi de c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs. auric.</hi>
                  </note> did not ſo much as couer them ſelues vvith ſheepes ſkinnes, but beinge verie noon-deuils DEMONIA MERIDIANA haue painted out them ſelues as Apoſtatas of nature, publiſhing their ſinnes like So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and not hiding the ſame; hell it ſelfe could not caſt forth more filth then the ſchoole of thoſe abhominable <hi>Pentapolitaines</hi> or
<hi>Gomorits.</hi> They haue digged out of the earth the bookes of impietie and ethnical
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:5177:37"/> corruptions vvhich our forefathers had buried. They haue thereof made commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, and put them in french for to infecte therwith the vvorld: An horrible thing, that they haue not bene aſhamed to call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues waldins: to write that they helpe them
<note place="margin">Beza imag.</note> ſelues with empoiſoning; with witche craft, withe Magick, and with the deueliſhe arte for to diſpatch them ſelues of their euil willers. I would neuer haue beleued that Sathan had bene ſo impudent, if I had not ſeen the ſame in their bokes. They do reuile all auncient fathers with ſhameful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iureis, exalting the olde heretikes ſo farre, that they call S. Herome a peruerſe ſpirit, <note place="margin">Cal. in har. eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> and wicked: &amp; IOVINIAN which was an heretike they call an holie man: and ſay, that S. Hierom and S. Auguſtin in that, that they did gainſey IOVINIAN were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues heretikes. And it is a wonderful doltiſh folie in them whom they haue bewitched, that they doe not recouer any ſpace of time, for to conſider their illuſions: and whereof it cometh that in their writinges do appeare ſo many iniureis, ſuch falſe accuſations, and lyes, and not any light of Charitie, or grief of ſcandel of their neighbours, turning al ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of diſorder in to mockery or matter of detraction, in their behauiours. The fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:5177:37"/> goddeſſe <hi>Ate</hi> in Homer, did neuer make ſo many calamities as they haue made where they haue paſſed by. If their ſectaries ſeing their ſteppes did caſt ther eyes towardes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for to conſider by the motion of vvhat ſpirit they haue burned our Churches, martired, cruellie our prieſtes, deſtroyed our howſes, &amp; committed a million of in humanities, they ſhould ſee that ſuch thinges be not the markes of the true church. The ſpirit of God is not in a tempeſt of wind ouerthrowing the monteignes and breaking the ſtones; it is not in a thundering commotion; it is not in in fier which doth diſtroy wher it paſſeth: it is in a ſound of a ſpirit, calme, and gentle, woorking no harme nor ruine, but creating a new &amp; reuiuing in ſuch ſort, as the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſayth that he did manifeſt him ſelf to Elias. As for the Catholike people, it is too true that there be manie wicked, yet there are alſo many that fear God, loue theyr neighbour, and endeuor to kepe them ſelues vndefiled of this world: which had rather loſe their goodes &amp; their liues then the grace of God. The catholike people is as the grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of a laborer full of ſheaues of corne, whereof their doth not appear to the eies but the chaffe: Yet if one come to threſhe the ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and put the graine bare apart, there
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:5177:38"/> wil be founde a good heape. I know men ſee not the good people goe to gether in troupes, but that the flud of corruption which hath ſwaie, hath ouerthrowen manie, and that it ſemeth, (as ſayth the Prophet) that Sathan doth reape the field and gather the vines, and that God doth not but gleane or leaze after him. But yet I ſaye there be a good number which doe ſet them ſelues againſt the euil, and continue ſtil ſtanding vpright, holding them ſelues faſtened to GOD and wil be raither cruſhed to pieces then to ſeperate them ſelues from him: VVho if they fall ſomtime by infirmitie, yet they riſe againe quickly, mainteining their cuſtome of weldoing, and praying vnto God inceſſantlie that he will fortifie them: and when they muſt reſolue them ſelues, will forſake all the reſpectes of the world for the honour of God.</p>
               <p>As for our prieſts it can not be diſſembled, but that there be dreedfull ſcandals, and all good people haue their hartes wounded to ſee the diſorders that be in them: thoſe men that deſerue high puniſhment haue there the higheſt honours, and the mindes of the comen people, which are moued more by by exemple, than by reaſon, doe fall by to much marking the maners of manye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:5177:38"/> But what ſo euer confuſion there be, yet are there ſome found not vnworthie, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed here and there, doing their charge with reuerence. The grief is that the greater parte doth ſurmount the better; and there are not to furniſhe euerie where. It is our parte to praye that when the Iudaſſes &amp; trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ſhal be gone into thir places, GOD will giue vs <hi>Mathiaſſes.</hi> for to ſupplie their romthes againe. In the mean tyme, good or bad as we haue them we honor them, as mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and diſpenſers of the miniſteries of God. We know that we muſt alwaies make diſtinction betwene the vocation and the perſon. In mines of golde and ſiluer, one ſhal not finde the golde all pure: there is but one litle vein vpon a grain of the earth: Yet men let not for that, to take that veine and leaue the earth. Now the golde and the ſiluer be the Sacramentes and the vvord of God: the earth is the corrupted maners.
<hi>The holines of the church co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth not in the perſons, but in the Sacramentes</hi> ſayth Optatus. The prieſtes for the reuerence of their prieſthood ought <note place="margin">Optatus.</note> to be as Melchiſedech without father, vvithout mother, vvithout genealogie, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.</note> kinges of peace and of Iuſtice: that is to ſay, all ſpiritual, al pure, all holie, vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fleaſhelie affection, as if they vvere
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:5177:39"/> deſcended from heauen, not ſubiect to the paſſions of men: yf they be not ſuch, if thei preach the good and do the euill, they be like the carpenters of the arke of Noe, which taking no care to ſaue them ſelues did not enter therin<hi>:</hi> or like the candle vvhich giueth light to others and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it ſelf; or as the markes which ſhew the vvay and ſturre not from theyr place. Noe did not caſt him ſelf in to the water be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the vncleanes of the beaſtes vvhich weare in the arke: ſo vve muſt not depart from the Church for the vices of men. If a ſike man ſhould refuſe the remedie of a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, for that the phiſition him ſelf is ſubict to the like diſeaſe, he were miſaduiſed. The grace of the Sacramentes is not of leſſe force for the euill life of a prieſt: and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie can not be impeached by the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of perſons. If the beames of the ſunne do not defile them ſelues paſſing by vncleane places; much leſſe doe the Sacramentes of god, wich be remedies purging al co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagions. A man muſt neuer ground his religion vpon the perfection of creatures: for that vvere idolatrie. It is vpon the vvord of God that he muſt make his foundation. And I vvill ſay more, that it vvas expedient for vs, to haue for our paſtors, men taken from among
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:5177:39"/> men, which be of fleſ he and blood as vve are, weake and vnperfect as wee, and can haue compſſion on vs, for to diſtribute the Sacraments according as our weaknes doth require. If God had giuen vs Angels for paſtors, they would haue required too great perfections of vs. God hath giuen to prieſtes the miniſterie of his giftes. It is of prieſtes that our Sauiour doth ſay, as thow haſt ſent me to the worlde, ſol I haue ſent them into the world. I haue giuen them thy word, and I do not praie onlie for them, but for thoſe which ſhall beleue in me by their word. How contemptible ſo euer the perſon of the prieſt be, I conſider God in him, and not the man: and honoring the contemptible man, in that he is the vicar of God, I honour God more, than if I honored a holie man which were perfect: becauſe I doe it not for any other reſpect than for the loue of God: where as in holie men, it is the holines of life &amp; the prerogatiue of vertues which maketh them venerable. To be ſhort, we muſt not onlie receiue Ieſus Chriſt in his own perſon, but we alſo muſt receiue the holie Ghoſt in his Church: As Ieſus Chriſt is the head, ſo the holie Ghoſt is the ſoule of the Churche; and the chaire of Ieſus Chriſt ſhall not haue leſſe priuileige than that of Moiſes. From Moiſes
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:5177:40"/> vnto the Meſſias, the Sinagogue alwayes taught the truth: ſo the chaire of Meſſias ſhal teach the truth, to the end of the world. The grace of the chaire is of that force, that the ſame doth conſtraine thoſe to ſay wel which do not wel: but manie in that chaire do the one &amp; the other. For concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this marke: Among Catholikes there be good people, &amp; all may be ſuch: but among heretikes there be none good, nor none can be.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> The tenth marke is <hi>the gloire of mirakles,</hi> which be diuine operations ſurmounting <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. <hi>Math.</hi> 10. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.
<hi>Mar. vlt. Haebr.</hi> 2. <hi>Aug. li. de vti.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>red. &amp;</hi> 22. <hi>de c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uit. Dei c.</hi> 8. <hi>Tert. l. de praeſ.</hi>
                  </note> the habilitie of all creatures, as to raiſe the dead, to make the blind to ſee, to helpe the lame, and to cure diſeaſes which are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralie incurable. And this marke is neceſſarie for to perſuade a new faith, or an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie ſending, euen according as the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and all the fathers doe teach. But neuer were there true miracles in the worlde but among the Iewes and the Catholikes: The Iewes haue not had anie, ſithens Ieſus Chriſt. The Mahometiſts haue neuer made anie: &amp; Mahomet ſayth in the Alcoran, that the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles haue bene giuen to Ieſus Chriſt, and the ſword to him. The Panimes alſo neuer wrought any true miracles. Thoſe wich they report touching an oxe and an Image vvhich did ſpeake, water caried in a ſiue by a veſtal
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:5177:40"/> virgin, a raſor that did cut a whetſtone, and <note place="margin">Tit. Liuius. Cicero. Val. Max.</note> ſuch like, be al light toyes tending not to the vinification or bettering of anie creature, but be ſecret trickes which the deuils might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilie doe for to amaze and to maintein the folies of Paganiſme. But true and liuelie miracles bringing ſound counfort to men, neuer Sathan nor his angels, nor the falſe prophets, nor the Panimes, nor the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes <note place="margin">Suetonius. Corn. Tacitus.</note> haue euer done any. Thoſe that SVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TONIVS and TACITVS haue written of Veſpaſian, that he did make one that was blinde to ſee with his ſpitle, and heale one that was lame, and an other that had a drie hande, thoſe be the miracles of Ieſus chriſte, which thoſe prophane perſons wold rob him of, for to attribute them to their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereur: and they them ſelues diſcouer their theft by their owne writtings. TACITVS doth write that the ſaide blind man ſayd to Veſpaſian, that he had in reuelation of the God Serapis, to come to him. Now the Panimes, which had not yet hearde then of IESVS Chriſt, did thinke that the Chriſtians did worſhip Serapis, as it doth appeare an epiſtle of the Empereur Adrian to Seruia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus conſul, as apeareth in <hi>Vopiſcus</hi> where he ſayth: that in the towne of Alexandria they that worſhippe Serapis were Chriſtians.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:5177:41"/> whereby one may ſee that the Author of the healing of that blind, was the God of the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. The cauſe of the error in the name <hi>Serapis,</hi> cometh of that, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> throughout al the world, men talked of the miracles that Ieſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles had done in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and the countres round about: and did not declare them according to the pure truth, as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monlie things which be done in countries fer of, be diſguiſed and altered by them vvhich report them: &amp; the Panimes at al times haue bene raſhe &amp; foliſhe to iudge of things to them vnknowen, giuing for hiſtorie that vvhich they did imagin, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their darknes, as it appeareth euen by the ſcripture it ſelf. Euen ſo the Siria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s being ouercome by the Iewes, ſaid that the God of the Iewes vvas the God of Mountanes, and
<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20. 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18.</note> that they muſt intrappe him in the valleis. Euen ſo <hi>Rapſaces</hi> did iudge that Ezechias had deſtroied the aultars of the God of the Iewes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he deſtroyed the idols. Likerwiſe the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caonians did call Barnabas Iupiter, &amp; S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Mercurie, for that he was the cheef ſpeaker. In like manner the Panimes in the time of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 14.</note> the Apoſtles vnderſtanding that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did vvorſhip Ieſus Chriſt in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, ſaid that they did vvoorſhippe Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and Bacchus. And aboue al the Panimes, Tacitus by his writings doth ſhewe him
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:5177:41"/> ſelf to be a manifeſt ſclanderer of matters <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tac. l.</hi> 4. <hi>hiſt.</hi>
                  </note> both Chriſtian and Iudaical. But yet to take the hiſtorie, as if there vvere no errour in the name of Serapis, and that the deed vvere auerred in the perſon of Veſpaſian<hi>:</hi> it vvas not a blinde man in deed, nor a lame man indeed which were healed by Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian. For Tacitus doth write that the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiciens aſſembled did ſaye, that the diſeaſe of thoſe two were curable: that in the one the facultie of ſight was not loſt; and that the ſame might come again, if they did take from him the impediments: As to the other, he ſayd that it was eaſye to helpe his legges. Therefore if the diſeaſes which naturalie might be healed, haue bene cured by the craft of the deuil: that is not a true miracle. And it is credible which Tertullian ſayth, that thoſe diſeaſes whereof the deuil, which
<note place="margin">Tert. in Apol.</note> did hinder in the one the vſe of the eie, and in the other the vſe of the legges, to the end that he might ſeme to heale, vvhen he did ceaſe to hurt, and to the ende that he might darken the true miracles of Ieſus Chriſt, and of the Apoſtles. The true, certen, euident, and vnforged miracles haue neuer bene but in the Catholike Church, in the vvhich, at all times according to neceſſarie occaſion God hath wrought them, in the beginning
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:5177:42"/> in infinite number: but ſithens, that he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie plant hauing caſt his rootes through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the earth, and hauing no more need of ſuch vvatering; they haue bene leſſe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented. for that it is not for the benefite of the Church to haue ſo often miracles. And yet not witſtanding for the ſpace of theſe thowſand yeres there hath no age paſſed without miraclcs in the Catholike Church authentiklie witneſſed, and with out gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying: as the miracles done by <hi>Tharaſius,</hi> S. Malachie, S. Bernard, S. Frauncis, S. Dominike, and others, which haue made the blinde to ſee, reſtored hearing to the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Antonin. part. hiſt. cap.</hi> 23.</note> deafe, holpen the lame, and raiſed the deade. And it is not much more then a hundred yeares from S. Vincent, he which did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert 25. thowſand Iewes and Saraſins, of whom 38. dead men weare reiſed from death to life. Anthoninus which was of his time hath written the ſame. And all the people, Chriſtians, Iewes, and Turkes did ſee the ſame. Of our time it hath bene written from the Indiens newlie diſcouered, that Francis Xauier prieſt, a Ieſuit hath healed ſome of the palſey, ſome deafe, ſome domme, ſome blinde: and raiſed one dead, and hath done other miracles, witneſſing that he was of the ſpirit of the Apoſtles: And all thoſe holie
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:5177:42"/> perſons were Catholikes. Manie haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that Caluin &amp; other new heretikes haue ſuborned poore people for to counterfait them ſelues to be dead, to the end that they might raiſe them again in the aſſemble of people, for to authoriſe their impietie: the which counterfaiting to be dead, haue dyed indeed in the act of their feyning, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of the deceiuers. In concluſion, the marke of the true miracles is not found in any place of the world, but in the Catholike Church. </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> The eleuenth marke, is the vnhappie end of the archeheretikes, &amp; of princes their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors, and the proſperitie of thoſe that haue defended the Church. I know how much a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt leane or truſt to this marke; I know that God doth ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpare the wicked, and doth fatten them vvith proſperities, &amp; ſhevv him ſelf more auſtere and hard to his true children, to the end to a vvake them again, and that they remain not ſetled in the earth. Therfore our faith hath other ſounde groundes ſufficient vvithout authoriſing her by euentes, vvhich may haue by the wil of God motiues vnto vs incomprehenſible: and may happen ſomtimes vvith diſaduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage (in reſpect of the vvorld) to the true children of God, as roddes and fatherlie
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:5177:43"/> chaſtiſementes. But vve ſee ordinarilie that God doth ſhew him ſelf ſo good a father, and ſo fauorable towardes thoſe vvhich be couragiouſe to defende his Church, that ouer and aboue the moſt happie eternitie, vvhich is aſſured vnto them, he doth reward them alſo temporallie: and ſtrikes vvith ignominie and calamities, thoſe vvhich be enemies to him. Among the Archeheretiks, Simon Magus caried by the deuil in the ayr, at the prayer of S. Peter did fall downe and all bruſed died ſhamefullie: Manicheus was flaine a liue by the king of Perſia. Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus did hang him ſelf: Arrius being about to goe into the Church, ſodeinlie died of an horrible death caſting out his intrailes: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius vvas eaten of vermin. Luther died ſodenlie the ſame night that at ſopper he had tippled ſquare, goſſiped, and made all the companie to laugh. Zvvinglius vvas ſlaine in vvarre againſt the Catholikes: Corolſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius ſlaine of a deuil by the teſtimonie of his own diſciples. Caluin died yet more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. Among princes, Iulian the Apoſtata was ſlaine from heauen, and his bodie vvithout buryenge vvas ſwalowed vp of the earth, Valens burned a liue of the Arrian Gothes vvhom he had fauored. Anaſtaſius vvas ſtriken vvith thunder: Hunerick king of
<pb facs="tcp:5177:43"/> Vandals eaten vvith vermin: The 3. Herods, as alſo Nero, Domitian, Maximin and all the other perſecutors of Chriſtians be miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablie dead, either be killing them ſelues, or being cruellie killed by their owne men. Contrariwiſe all the Emperours and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like kinges which haue defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the church, haue bene glorious in the vvorld: God hath made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phe ouer their enemies, &amp; hath giuen them their deſires. The examples of Conſtantin, of Theodoſius the elder &amp; yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, of Honorius &amp; of others, doth proue the ſame. So longe as
<hi>Heraclius</hi> vvas a good catholike, he proſpered againſt the Perſians: after that he bekame an heretike, he vvas vnhappie and died miſerablie: Likewiſe Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinian. And to be, ſhort, ſithens that the Emperours of the eaſt, did vvithdraw them ſelues from the Romain Church, they grew from daie to daie in decaie, vvaxing weakar and weakar till they loſt the Empire. It is apparent that the Emperours of the weſt haue floriſ hed more or leſſe, according as their deuocion vvas more or leſſe to the church: As for Fraunce vve can not denie that euer it hath bene in greater glorie and more redowted to the world, than when it vvas a refuge to Popes; and hath neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined ſo much as vvhen it hath bene againſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:5177:44"/> them. And of our kings, thoſe which haue done moſt for the Romain Church, haue bene the moſt happie, moſt beloued of the people, and moſt dreadful to their enemies. In our time, in the yere 1531. the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Suiſſers had fiue battailes againſt the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retik Suiſſers, and in them all the Catholikes did vanquiſhe the heretikes: &amp; making fina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie a peace, in the firſt article, the heretikes did write this clauſe: that from thenſe forth they would leaue in peace their confederates concerning the point of their true indoubted and catholike faith. And the catholikes this clauſe: that they vvould leaue their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates in peace touching the point of their faith, vvithout adding this vvords <hi>true, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted, Catholike.</hi> In Germanie 1547. Charles the fifte vvith a ſmall number had a marueilous victoire of the Lutherans, which had an armie of more then threeſcore thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men. In Fraunce the Catholikes haue alwaies for the moſt part ouercome the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, as at the battell of dreuz, of Ierna, of Mountcounter, and ſeldome or neuer haue the heretikes in iuſte battel ouercome the catholikes, neither in Fraunce, nor in flaunders, nor in Almaine, nor els vvhere: and vve ſhal ſee doubtles (vvith the grace of God) that thoſe vvhich at this daie put
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:5177:44"/> them ſelues in force to defend the Church, God ſhal croune them vvith honour and glorie, and ſhal heape vnto them goods, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperities, and temporal bleſſings, &amp; ſhal cauſe his vvrath and all maledictions and ſhames to raigne vpon the perſecutors, and vpon the ſecret traitors vvhich doe fauour he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie.</p>
               <p>The twelueth marke, is the vnion of the members vvith their ſoueraine head, which is the ſucceſſor of S. Peter, in the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the vniuerſall Church. Our Sauiour being deſirous to giue vs ſuer and ſetteled centre in the ſphere of his church, from the vvhich all the lines of the doctrine of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be drawen to the circumference of the vvorld, did choſe the chaire of S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is to ſay, the place conſecrated by the ſeat and martirdom of S. Peter, the vvhich by prerogatiue of honour he did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point to be head of the vnitie of his Church, making him, not his ſucceſſor (for it is IESVS CHRIST him ſelf, vvhich is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the onlie true head of his Churche, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining vnmouable and immortal, and vvhich neuer ſhal haue ſucceſſor, making it fruitful alwais him ſelf onlie, by his holie ſpirit.) But making him his depute, lifte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and vice gerent in earth, in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:5177:45"/> miniſterie and ſoueraine iuriſdiction of his Church, and after him all his ſucceſſors in the ſame ſorte: So that the ſoueraine Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes be vicars of IESVS CHRIST, and not ſucceſſors: and ſucceſſors of S. Peter not his vicars. who ſo euer wil take from the church, that Monarchie called the <hi>vicareige of</hi> IESVS Chriſt, he vvold haue a floke vvithout a paſtor: an armie vvithout a leader<hi>:</hi> a bodie vvithout a head: a building vvithout foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: and the ſtarres vvithout their ſonne; that is to ſave, he would haue the diſperſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the flocke, the diſcomforture of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, the death of the bodie, the ouerthrow of the building, the darkning of the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res; he would haue a confuſed chaos, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered &amp; voyd of all proportion, and an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie or gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, more horrible, more confuſed and more diſordered, than the bottomleſſe pit it ſelf; he deſerueth not to be heard. God vvhich is the author of order and not of confuſion, vvhich hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an order among the Angels, wil not that we goe mingle mangle in the ſocietie of this world. We know wel as touching the power of the order, vvhich concerneth the real bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of the perſon of Ieſus Chriſt, all prieſtes be equal to S. Peter, and to the ſoueraine biſhoppe in the prieſthood: But as touching
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:5177:45"/> the Iuriſdiction vvhich doth concerne the bodie miſticall of the church, there it is where there are different degrees, and where one ſoueraine head of all prieſtes is requiſit, which may hold the principalitie ouer all the Ckurch. Who ſo euer diſſembleth to
<note place="margin">Thirtie tvvo prerogatiues of S, Peter.</note> ſee in the text of the goſpel the principalitie of S. Peter, and of his ſucceſſors, he is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel to light, and fleeth the truth, of ſet pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and doth ſhew that he is ſtirred by the wickednes of a poiſoned hart: for theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues of S. Peter, which are witneſſed in the goſpel are to be conſidered. Firſt that S. Matthew manifeſtlie and expreſſelie hath <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.</note> giuen to S. Peter the title of chief of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, And all the Euangeliſtes, making men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy college of the Apoſtles, doe giue alwaies the firſt place to S. Peter. That S. Peter is only he among the Apoſtles to whom our ſauiour hath chaunged the name, and hath giuen him one of his owne names, moſt famous, wherbie he is often ſignified, noted, or deſigned in the ſcriptures (that is to ſaie) <hi>the rocke:</hi> for in thoſe two that were ſurnamed ſonnes of thunder, the name was not chaunged, they had onlie the gyft of vehemencie. Now God did neuer put new name, but when he made ſome great new benefite in the vvorld, giuing vvith the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:5177:46"/> name the efficacie of the which it doth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie: as naming Abraham he gaue him to be made a father of manie nations: euen ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Peter, he gaue him the firmnes of the
<hi>rocke</hi> and of <hi>ſtone,</hi> for to ground vpon him ſome great new building. Let it be alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered that S. Peter is only he among the Apoſtles: to whom the father euerlaſting did reueale, that Ieſus vvas Chriſte, the ſonne of the liuing God. For al the other holding their peace, &amp; ſuffering the ignorant opino<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people to preuaile which had ſo baſe an imagination of IESVS Chriſt, that they did eſteme him only, for either Elias, for the zeale of the lawe; or Hieremie for the holines of lyfe: or Ihon Baptiſt by reaſon of his baptizing: or ſome prophet for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile the things to come: S. Peter only put him ſelf forward not hauing reſpect to the ſubſtance of fleaſhe and blood; but paſſing on beyond thoſe corporal and humain thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, by reuelation of the ſoueraigne father he did ſee with the eies of the minde the ſonne of the liuing God; and confeſſed the gloire of his deitie, pronouncing with hart &amp; mouth theeſe wordes, or rather that ſound of the diuinitie and humanitie of IESVS Chriſt: <hi>Thow art Chriſt the ſonne of the liuing God:</hi> as if he had ſaid, thow art not Elias,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:5177:46"/> which was taken vp into heauen, thou art Ieſus Chriſt which art deſcended from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for to lift vp man from the earth: thou art not Hieremie, or Ihon baptiſt ſanctified in the woumbes of thir mothers, But Ieſus Chriſt ſanctifying the world: thou art not a prophet to whom are reuealed the things to come, but Ieſus Chriſt which haſt preſent in thy ſight all eternitie. Thoſe woordes, be verie high, but the ſenſe vnderſtood by S. Peter, is yet much higher: And it was neceſſarie that it ſhould ſo be, that he which ought to hold the chaire of Ieſus Chriſt, for to teach all the world the true religion, ſhould haue that loftines of faith, that greatenes of knowleige, that feruour of loue, and confeſſe the ſame, by the which his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, as Ieſus Chriſt, had made him to know God: ſo S. Peter had made Ieſus Chriſt to be knowen: Whervpon Ieſus Chriſt hath therfore loued him aboue all the other, hath therfore declared him verie happie and hath giuen him that greate participarion of his name, <hi>rocke.</hi> And to the end that that name ſhould not be void and idle, he promiſed him rhat vpon that ſtone, he would build his Church, and that the gates of hell ſhould neuer preuaile againſt the ſame: that he would giue him the keies of the kingdome
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:5177:47"/> of heauen, and that all that he ſholde bynde and vnbynde in earth ſhould be bound and vnbound in heauen: he hath not ſpoken of giuing the keyes to the other Apoſtles. So the church is builded vpon the faith and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of S. Peter: And the faith which is the ſeed of our regeneration is called the <hi>faith of</hi> S. <hi>Peter:</hi> Let that alſo be conſidered which is ſpoken of in S. Luke, that the people preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 5.</note> on our ſauiour for to heare the word of God: our Sauiour ſeing neare the lake two ſhippes, went vp into the one which belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 5. Io. 21.</note> to S. Peter, where being ſet, he did teache the people. And thoſe that ſailed in the other ſhippe tranſported them ſelues into that of S. Peter, with Ieſus Chriſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Let it be further conſidered that the two miracles. done by our ſauiour in the taking of fiſhes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> were done in the ſhip of S. Peter, and by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of S. Peter. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> That S. Peter, alſo is only he among the Apoſtles, that our ſauiour made goe vpon the waters: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
                  <hi>for whom</hi> only he paied tribute: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
                  <hi>for whom</hi> only in particular he praied to his father, to the end his faith ſhould not fayle: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
                  <hi>to whom</hi> onlie he gaue charge to confirme the faith of his brethere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
                  <hi>of whom,</hi> as head of others, he did require more loue then of others. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 
                  <hi>whoſe</hi> feet <hi>he did</hi> firſt vvaſhe accordng to S. Auguſtin: to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:5177:47"/> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/>
                  <hi>whom</hi> he did firſt appeare after his reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
                  <hi>to whom</hi> only he foretould his death and death on the croſſe: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> 
                  <hi>to whom</hi> onlie he ſaid three tymes feed &amp; gouerne my ſheepe, meaning his Church<hi>: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> whome</hi> more preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelie than others he commaunded to folowe him: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> 
                  <hi>who onlie,</hi> vvhen the diſciples were ſcandalized at the vvordes of our ſauiour, ſaying that he vvolde giue his bodie to eate, anſwered for all the Apoſtles, and ſayd: <hi>Lorde thow haſt the wordes of life euerlaſtlng, and we beleeue the ſame:</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> 
                  <hi>whom onlie</hi> among all the diſciples our ſauiour did baptize with his owne handes. Firſt Euodius immediat ſucceſſor of S. Peter in the Biſhopryke of <note place="margin">Euodius in lib.</note> Anthioche hath written, that our ſauiour <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> did baptize onlie the virgin his mother among women; and S. Peter onlie among men, and that S. Peter did baptize S. Andrew S. Iames, S. Ihon, and the others: That S. Perer alſo as head of the Apoſtles, after the aſcenſion of our ſauiour did aſſemble the church for to chuſe an Apoſtle in the place of Iudas:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> That S. Peter after the ſending of the holie ghoſt, did firſt preache and conuert in two ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s eight thowſand ſoules: That he <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 1.</note> did the firſt miracle on the lame man, which was at the gate of the temple. That he as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraine iudge did condemne the fraude and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:5177:48"/> hipocriſie of Ananias and Saphira, whom he did kill with his woord: That he knew and did condemne the firſt notable Archehere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike Simon Magus: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> that to him was directed, as to the head, the viſion of that ſheete, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> Let downe from heauen, hauing of all ſortes of beaſtes, and comandement to preache to the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> gentiles;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> the which viſion doth concerne the direction of the vniuerſal Church: that for him as head of the Church prayer was made without intermiſſion in al the Church,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 15.</note> which is not ſayd of anie of the others.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> That he in the Councel of the Apoſtles did ſpeake firſt as head:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> That he in the moſt holie <hi>Creed</hi> of the Apoſtles did begin firſt, by that high woorde <hi>Credo,</hi> therby making the chriſtian religion, a religion of faith, for whoſe ſake S. Paul ſaith that he went vp expreſſelie into Hieruſalem;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> note alſo, that S. Peter him ſelfe doth teſtifie, that God choſe him emong the Apoſtles, that by his mouth the Gentiles ſhould heare the woord of the Goſpel, and beleeue: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> Let it be alſo conſidered that after that the twelue Apoſtles had receiued the holie Ghoſte and the gifte of all tounges, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing diſtributed among them ſelues all the earth, therin to plant euerie one in his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt; S. Peter as head of the twelue, is ſent to the head of the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:5177:48"/> world, to the Queene of cities, the cheif ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Romain Empire; to the end, that the law of trueth which did reuele, it ſelf for the ſaluation of all people, might ſprede it ſelf abroode more eaſilie from the head to all the bodie of the world: and vvhere the vvorld had the head of his Empire, there the prince of the Apoſtles hath had his ſeate: in the citie of Rome: in the which (hauing firſt giuen order to the affaires of the Eaſt) he comes him ſelf to make his aboade, for to forme and ſet in order the affaires of the weſt, and of all the world: where hauing ended his courſe before the tyme of his death <note place="margin">2.
<hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note> Ieſus Chriſt made vnto him yet one preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue more,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> 
                  <hi>by appearing</hi> vnto him, and ſaying to him, that he would be glorified by his martirdome within the citie of Rome:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> 
                  <hi>Let it</hi> be further conſidered that the Churches founded by S. Peter, (that is to ſaye <hi>Antioche,</hi> and
<hi>Alexandria)</hi> haue bene named the chief <note place="margin">In Con. Calced.</note> Patriarchal Churches, and did goe before all the others in the Councels. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> Let it be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Optatus lib.</hi> 2,</note> that in the primatiue Church, in the teſtimonial letters that they gaue to thoſe that went in to farre cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, &amp; did chaunge their habitations, to the end they might be receiued where they went to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sidon Apol. l.</hi> 7. <hi>ep.</hi> 2.</note> there was put downe in ſubſcription after
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:5177:49"/> the firſt letters of the names of the father, of the ſonne and of the holie ghoſte, the firſt letter of the name of S. Peter, for witnes, that ſuch a one was Catholike. <hi>Finallie</hi> let it be conſidered that the Church hath made a feaſt, or holie dare of the chaire of S. Peter, fos to praiſe God for the ſoueraign benefit that he hath done to his Church, to giue him a chaire eminent aboue the others which ſhold alwais be certein, vnto whom al the world may haue recourſe, &amp; of whom all the world ought to be inſtructed as
<hi>ſayth Optatus:</hi> the which feaſt is very auncient. For Bede and S. Auguſtin, make mention therof. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Optat. li.</hi> 2. <hi>Bed. in Thetl. Aug. ſer.</hi> 15.
<hi>de ſanct.</hi>
                  </note> But in none of the other Apoſtles are the prerogatiues found to be called of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our into the felouſhippe of his name, and of his office and paſtoral care: and euen of his death: to be the mouth, of the other Apoſtles in all occurrent affaires, nor the other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues, the which haue bene attributed of all the aucients, to the ſupremacie and principalitie of S. Peter: which being eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in S. Peter, it is ſuperfluous to ſpeake of them in his ſucceſſors. For it is well knowen that our ſauiour giuing a head to his Church hath not intended to giue onlie the ſame for the time of S. Peter; as if the Church had had no need therof after him. But it is the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:5177:49"/> cuſtome of GOD to make the firſt formes of thinges as moulds, and afterwardes to let the ſame be continewed by ſucceſſion: &amp; propagation according to their nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="testimonies">
               <head>TESTIMONIES OF THE fathers, and of Councels, for the ſupremacie of S. Peter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ſhould not be neede full to procede here any farder. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe heretikes be ſo impudent liars, as to ſey that the auncient fathers haue neuer geuen to S. Peter nor to his ſucceſſours Biſhops of Rome, thoſe names of <hi>Prince,</hi> of <hi>Head,</hi> or of
<hi>Soueraigne,</hi> I will bring forth ſome teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies for to confound them.</p>
               <p>S. Irene, being nere to the tyme, of the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi>
3.</note> Apoſtles, ſayd. That it muſte neceſſarilie be, that all the vniuerſall Church, that is to ſay, all the faithfull which be in all the world ſhould reſorte to the Romain Church for her moſt high principalitie, and doth adde, that in this Church, the true traditions of the Apoſtles, and the faith vvhich geueth life, hath always bene kept.</p>
               <p>S. Ciprian, he which forſaketh the Chaire of ſainct Peter vpon the vvhich the
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyp. l. de v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ita. eccl. &amp; ep.</hi> 55. 69.</note> Church is founded, doth he think to be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:5177:50"/> in the Church? Moreouer he doth call S. Peter the head, the fountain the Roote, and the matrice of the Church: He doth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to him the ſupremacie of the Apoſtles in preheminence of excellent grace, he ſaith that vnfaithfulnes can not haue acceſſe to the chaire of S. Peter, and that the cauſe of all hereſies procedeth of this, that men be not obedient to one onelie Biſhop, vicar of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Hierome:</hi> Among the twelue Apoſtles, one ys choſen head for to take away all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron. cont. Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a.</hi> 71.</note> of ſchiſme, And being in the holy place of our lords natiuitie in Iurie, he did write to Rome to Pope Damaſus in theſe termes: Loe here the faith which I haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">Hieron. ad Damaſ. pap.</note> in the Catholike Church: If I doe erre in any maner of faſſion as Ignorant, or as miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſed: I deſire that you correcte me, ſithens that you haue the ſeate and the faith of S. Peter. And if you allow my confeſſion, I proteſt then bouldelie againſt whoſoeuer ſhal reproue me: that I am not ignorant, &amp; that he is wicked or an heretike. Your citie of Rome is happie, where the faith of the fathers kepeth it ſelfe vncorrupted. Here the euil children haue conſumed their Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie. Here the good graine is degenerate into cockle, whereas your Rome being all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:5177:50"/> fertile with diuine ſeede, watered with heauenlie graces, fructified in one ſelfe ſame puritie. Now in the vveſt, the ſonne of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice doth riſe: Here in the Eaſt, that Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vvich did fall from heauen, hath ſet his throne: I pray yow therefore to teach me that which I ought to keepe ſecret or vtter, concerning the fayth, I ſhunne euerie here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, I folowe yow onelie, I am the ſheepe vvhich demaundeth ſuccour of the Paſtour, I ſpeake to the ſucceſſour of the fiſher, to the diſciple of the Croſſe, I hould me to your holines, that is to ſay, to the chaire of S. Peter. I know that vpon this Rocke the Church is gronded, that vvhoſoeuer out of this houſe doth eate the Lambe, he is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned, he is not of Ieſus Chriſt: he is of Antechriſt. Moreouer he calleth the Romain Church a verie pure fountain, vvhich doth not receiue Illuſions againſt the faith: vvhich hath neuer noriſhed hereſie: vvhich hath allwayes continued immaculate, Ruffinus <note place="margin">Ruffin. in ſym.</note> ſayd alſo that neuer hereſie tooke beginning at Rome.</p>
               <p>S. Auguſtine: who knoweth not the principalitie of the Apoſtleſhip of S. Peter is
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. tract.</hi> 55. <hi>&amp;</hi> 124. <hi>Ep.</hi> 164. <hi>lib. de Bapt.</hi>
                  </note> to be preferred before any Biſhoprike? The Principalitie of the Apoſtolike chaire, hath allwayes had force in the Romain Church:
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:5177:51"/> S. Peter as concerning his perſon, by nature, was but a man, by grace a Chriſtian; But by more abundant grace, that on &amp; ſelfe ſame man, is the cheef Apoſtle: and for the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie of his Apoſtleſhip doth repreſent the vniuerſall Church. And ſpeaking of the Repentance of S. Peter: Our Lord (ſayth he) hath healed the diſeaſe of all the bodie in the head<hi>:</hi> and in the verie toppe of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. ſer.</hi>
144. <hi>de paen. Pet.</hi>
                  </note> the Church. And praying for S. Peter he hath prayed for all; for that the benefit of the head doth redounde to the people. He doth moreouer call the Pope <hi>father of the Chriſtian</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. in q. vet. &amp; nou. Teſt. q.</hi> 75.
<hi>Amb. ſer.</hi> 47.</note> 
                  <hi>people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. Ambroſe ſaith, our Lord aſcending into the onely ſhip of the Church, whereof S. Peter is the gouernour, that ſhip doth ſo ſwimme in the high See of the world, that the vvorld periſhing, ſhe ſhall kepe ſafe: (as did the Arke of Noe in the ſhipwrake of the world) thoſe whome ſhe ſhall haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. And as the flud being paſſed, the doue brought into the Arke the ſigne of peace: euen ſo after the burning of the vvorld, to thoſe whom the Arke of the Church ſhall repreſent, Ieſus Chriſt ſhall bringe the ſigne of his peace &amp; of his Ioye. He ſayth further, that Peter is the vicar of the Loue of Ieſus Chriſte towards vs: that he is the ſtone of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:5177:51"/> Churches, which, as an vnmouable Rocke, conteineth the heape and Ioining together of all Chriſtian building: That, not S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew but S. Peter hath had the primacie and care of Churches. Optatus emong the markes, of the true church putteth the chaire
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Optat. li.</hi> 2.</note> of S. Peter for the firſt, and cheefe. There is (ſaith he) but one onely chaire, which hath bene ſet at Rome, where the head of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, S. Peter hath bene preſident: in whom the vnitie of the chaire is kept of all, and he ſhould be a Schiſmatike, and wicked man who againſt that ſingular chaire; would ſet vp an other.</p>
               <p>S. Leo. Of all the world onely S. Peter <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leo ſer.</hi> 3.</note> is choſen preſident for the vocation of the gentiles, &amp; for all the fathers of the church: And allthough there be many prieſtes and many paſtours, emong the people of God: Yet S. Peter doth gouern them all: And it was ſo ordained by great prouidence, that in euery place there ſhould be one head: in the great townes other ſuperiour heads ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more ample Iuriſdiction; by whoſe meanes the care of the vniuerſall Church ſhould come to the ſeat of S. Peter: and that nothing ſhould be diſagreing with his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne head.</p>
               <p>Proſper. Rome is the ſeat of S. Peter:
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:5177:52"/> A Hatchet of hereſies: the head of all the <note place="margin">Proſp. lib. de Ingratis.</note> world: That which ſhe can not poſſeſſe by Armes, ſhe doth hold the ſame by religion.</p>
               <p>S. Gregorie: It is moſt cleere vnto al thoſe that know the Goſpel, that the care &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalitie of the whole Church hath bene gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to <hi>S, Peter, Prince</hi> of all the Apoſtles, by the voice of our Lord him ſelfe.</p>
               <p>S. Bede. <hi>S. Peter</hi> hath ſpecially had the keyes <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bed. in vigil.</hi> S. <hi>Andr.</hi>
                  </note> of the kingdome of heuen, &amp; the principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Iudicial power, to the ende that, al the faithful which are in the world, might vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that whoſoeuer doth ſeparat him ſelf from the vnitie of the faith, &amp; of the ſocietie of S. Peter, he can not be abſolued from the bandes of his ſinnes, nor be brought in at the gate of the kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p>S. Bernard, A man doubtles very holy, and very farre of from al flattery, obſeruing euery where the ſeueritie of brotherly correction, vſed theſe termes to <hi>Pope Innocent:</hi> we muſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ber. ep.</hi> 190.</note> bring to your Apoſtleſhip all the perils and ſcandals which riſe in the Church, being a thing mete that the detriments of the faith may be reſtored in that place, where the faith ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not receiue detrime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: for this is the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue of that ſeat. And to <hi>Pope Eugen.</hi> Thou <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernar. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de conſider.</hi>
                  </note> art the great prieſt, the ſoueraign Biſhop, Prince of Biſhops, Inheretour of the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:5177:52"/> In Primacie Abel: In Patriarchie Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham: Moiſes in authoritie: S. Peter in power: Ieſus chriſt in vnctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The others haue euerie one flokes aſſigned a part: to the all flockes are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, &amp; thou art not onely Paſtour of Sheepe, but Paſtour of Paſtours.</p>
               <p>Among the Greekes, Origen ſaith that the gouernement of the Church hath bene gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to S. Peter: that S. Peter is the cheefe or head of the Apoſtles, hauing more power and perfection then others.</p>
               <p>S. Greg. Nazianz. The diſciples of Ieſus Chriſt, all great &amp; excellent, &amp; wourthie to be heades, haue neuer the leſſe bene very wel content, to be put behind S. Peter vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe faith the church hath her foundation.</p>
               <p>Io. Chriſoſt. Our lord hath ſhed his blood <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſt. lib.</hi>
2. <hi>de ſacerd.</hi>
                  </note> for to get together the ſheepe of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the charge to S. Pe. &amp; to his ſucceſſours. Hieremie was father to one nation, but Ieſus Chriſt hath ſet S. Peter ouer all the world.</p>
               <p>S. Baſil: Ieſus chriſt him ſelf is trulie the <note place="margin">Baſil. de paenit.</note> immouable Rocke, S. Peter is ſo by Reaſon of that Rocke: Ieſus chriſt giuing him his dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, doth not ſpoyle him ſelfe of them, nor hath any thing leſſe.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theoph. in illae verba</hi> Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma frat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es tuos.</note> Theoph. bringeth in our ſauiour ſpeaking to S. Pet. Thou who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue made Prince of the diſciples; who after thou hadeſt denied me,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:5177:53"/> haſt again receiued the Primacie of all, the preheminence of the whole world, who art after me the ſtone, and the foundation of the Church, confirme the others, and be to them a good example of repentance.</p>
               <p>S. Thomas citeth out of S. Cirill theſe woordes, As Ieſus Chriſt hath receiued of the father the ſcepter of the Gentiles; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo hath he plainlie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted it to S. Peter and to his ſucceſſors; and hath not geuen that which is his own to any other but vnto S. Peter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiphaneus: Oecumenius: Euthymius:</hi> and all the reſt of the auncient Greekes, doe ſpeak of this matter conformably to the Latines<hi>:</hi> And Origen, and S. Hierome haue applied that place of S. Paule to the Romaines, <hi>(your faith is preached through the vniuerſall world:)</hi> in the ſence of the principalitie of the Romain Church: As if S. Paul ſhould giue thancks to GOD for the conuerſion of that place, which ſhould be the oracle of the vniuerſal Church, and wherof dependeth the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the whole whorld.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ephrem the Syrian</hi> ſaith, that, <hi>as Moiſes</hi> was head of the ſocietie of the Hebrewes; euen ſo was S. Peter of the Church of Chriſtians: And as the one was Prince of the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: ſo the other is likewiſe head of the new.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:5177:53"/> One Eritrianus in the time of Emperour Emmanuel; It doth appear manifeſtlie by euidence of the thing it ſelfe, that our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour hath appointed S. Peter Prince &amp; head for euer, not onely of the Latines and of Greekes, but of Armenians, of Arabians, of Iewes, of Madianites, of all the people of the Eaſt, and of the Weſt, of the South, &amp; of the North.</p>
               <p>The General Councels, which be as it were, the cheefe, ſeat of the holy Ghoſte, doe teſtifie the Primacie of the chaire of S. Peter, as it doth appeare in the firſt Councel of Nice, where it is ſayd that the Romain <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil.</hi> Nice.</note> Church is the Rule of the others.</p>
               <p>In the Councel of Calcedon, where Pope Leo is caled Biſhop of the vniuerſal Church,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chncil. Cal.</hi> 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.</note> to whom the keping of Gods vineyarde was committed, by our ſauiour.</p>
               <p>In the Councel of Conſtantinople, where <hi>Menas</hi> the Patriarche was preſident, it is ſaid: <note place="margin">Concil. Conſt.</note> we folowe the Sea Apoſtolike, &amp; it we obey, with them which communicate with it, we communicate: thoſe which are condemned by it, we condemne alſo.</p>
               <p>In the ſeuenth Synod of Carthage the ſeat of S. Peter hath primacie through al the world, being head of all the Churches of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:5177:54"/> In the Councel of Laterane<hi>:</hi> where the Greekes &amp; the Latines were. In the general Councel of <hi>Lions,</hi> &amp; in the Councel of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conci. Lat. c.</hi> 5.</note> by conſent of the Greekes &amp; of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, it is ſayd &amp; defined, that the holie Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike Seate and Biſhopricke of Rome, doth hold the Primacie ouer all the vniuerſal worlde, that the Pope is the true vicar of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, father and doctor of all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and head of all the Church.</p>
               <p>He ſhould make a great volume, which would gather together all the teſtimonies of the ſupremacie of S. Peter, &amp; of his ſucceſſors ouer the Church. This point was ſo cleere in the primitiue church, that certain heretikes, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> 5.
<hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>act. coll. Carthag.</hi>
                  </note> for to procure authoritie to their ſect, did faigne to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion with the Romain Church, ſo farre forth, that the <hi>Donatiſtes</hi> did ſuborn a Biſhop of their ſect, whom they cauſed to remain at Rome ſecretely, that they might ſay that they had that marke of the true church, which is of the chaire of S. Pet. And they ſuborned an other, which did pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Optat. lib.</hi> 2.</note> with ſome raſkall fugitiues of the citie of Rome coming fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thenſe. for to proue by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he was biſhop of Rome &amp; ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of S. Peter, but theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions being conuicted of this falſhood were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded and made ridiculous.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:5177:54"/> The Emperours the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues haue acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged the biſhop of Rome to be head of the vniuerſal Church: and they haue called him, <hi>Paſtor of Paſtors, father of fathers,</hi> and the <hi>toppe of the crown of the Clergie.</hi> And that ſo publik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, as the Paymin Authors make mention therof, as it appeareth in <hi>Amianus Mancellinus.</hi> which named
<hi>Pope Liberius</hi> ſouerain Biſhop of the Chriſtian law, and the <hi>Emperour Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> cauſed S. Athanaſius Biſhop of Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria to be ſent to the ſame Pope, of purpoſe to cauſe him to be condemned by him which hath the ſoueraign authoritie ouer the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
               <p>Thus by theſe teſtimonies as wel of the Goſpel, as of the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fathers, &amp; Councels, and by the practiſe of the Church it ſelfe, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens the Apoſtles to this day, it is manifeſt that there hath bene one ſouerai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> head in the miniſterie of the Church, vicar of the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain head eſſential, Ieſus Chriſt, and ſucceſſor of S. Peter, in that vicareige: to whom al Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes which are diſperſed throughout the world, are ioyned as members to their head.</p>
               <p>Loe here 12. markes, of the true church, That is to ſay, 1. The poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; propertie of the name <hi>Catholike</hi> 2. The ſucceſſion of the Apoſtolike prieſthood,
3. Antiquitie, 4. The long co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance without interruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 5. The
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:5177:55"/> largenes of the kingdome: 6. The victorie of the whole world, by efficacie of doctrine, 7. The conformitie in doctrine with the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, 8. The holynes of doctrine, 9. The holines of life of the poſſeſſours: 10. The gloire of miracles: 11. The Infelicitie of the impugners, and proſperitie of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectours: 12. And the vnion of the members with their head, the ſucceſſour of S. Peter. Theſe are compriſed in fower woordes of the
<hi>Creed,</hi> that is to ſay, in that ſhe is <hi>one, Holy: Catholike.</hi> and
<hi>Apoſtolike.</hi> I doe not enter here into the groundes of the doctrin of the Catholike Church; The principal ſcope of this preſent treatiſe, was onely to ſhew that out of the Catholike Church, man can not be ſaued whatſoeuer thing he doth, whereunto I haue added theſe outeward, markes, the which without farder diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be ſufficient to euery Chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to reſolue him ſelfe, touching all difficulties whatſoeuer, for all the controuerſies which haue bene, are, and euer ſhal be, in the faith, doe reſt therein: and are reduced to that onely head, to finde the true Church. Which being ones found, a man is out of all hazard and peril of errour. For all agree vpon this principle, that there is but one Church: and that the ſame can not erre, being (as
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:5177:55"/> ſaith S. Paul) <hi>The piller and ſeur grounde of truth.</hi> And therefore, whoſoeuer ſhall doubt of any thing, (as of Sacramentes, of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation of ſaincts, of praying for the dead, or of any other point of lerning) he muſt onely marke that which the Church doth teach thereof, and then, therevpon to reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue him ſelfe more aſſuredly, then if an Angel of heauen were deſcended expreſſely, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme him of the ſame. And euery other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation which ſhal call it ſelfe the church teaching the contrary, muſt needes be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced of falſehood, of being ſent from ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, of hereſie, and of impietie.</p>
               <p>All the markes of the Catholike Church are euidenly found in the Romain Church: The reſpect of the name <hi>Romain,</hi> is not to the town of Rome but the to chaire of S. Peter, which hath that highnes of glory, to haue bene cheefely and eſpecially priuileged by the prayer and promiſe of our ſauiour, who prayed for S. Peter, to that ende that his faith might not faile: and founding vpon him his Church, hath promiſed vnto him that the proud gates of hel ſhall neuer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uail againſt her, as in fact we ſee that ſathan hath ouercome the Churches of the other Apoſtles, and ouerthrowen their chaire, In <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> in
<hi>Epheſus,</hi> and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:5177:56"/> els where: But not the chaire wherewith S. Peter hath innobled the citie of Rome, This Church is onely, inuincible, inſupplantable, immouable fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her foundation: It is ſhe that hath born away the victory of the whole world. She hath deſtroyed Paganiſme, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen Idolatrie, expelled al hereſies, tamid kingdomes &amp; Empires, ouercome the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, driuen away the darkenes of the world, &amp; hath gained to god all men of good will. She hath troden down, and always ſhal tread down the head of ſathan: She hath ben euer ſithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s S. Peter, an obiect vnto the world very apparant, as a mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, A burning light not to be quenched, and an infallible Pole ſtarre, directing the way of God. To her onely in the troubleſome and tempeſtous ſea of variable opinions of men, we muſt haue regard. She is the quickening plant that God hath planted in earth, hauing her Roote in heauen: Yt is not poſſible for men to root her out, no more than it is to throw downe God from his heauenlie ſeat, vpon whom ſhe is founded. All the hereſies of the world haue bent them ſelues againſt that Church: Titans, Hypocrites, and euel Chriſtians haue aſſaulted her, but ſhe remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth victorious, ouer all her enemies, not by
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:5177:56"/> the merits of men, but by the efficacie of that prayer which our ſauiour made to his father for the faith of S. Peter, and to make his promiſe effectuall; The promiſes of the truth it ſelfe can not be vaine. Ieſus Chriſt ſayd of the temple of Hieruſalem, that there ſhould not one ſtone remayne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other: and ſo it came to paſſe, The Iewes edeuon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them ſelues with might and maine to build the ſame again, but fier came from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and placed it ſelf in the foundations, for to hinder their intrepriſe. He ſaid of his church, that it ſhould endure as long as the world ſhal remain, And men doe ſee that hither to ſhe remaneth as long as the world hath indured: heauen and earth ſhall paſſe, but the woordes of our Sauiour ſhall not paſſe; Let theſe wicked Spirites, heretikes. Schiſmatikes, Hypocrites, and deueliſhe men, lay their embuſhes, conſpire, make warre, and doe all they can againſt that Church, yet ſhal they get nothing. They fight againſt the prayer and promiſe of our Sauiour<hi>:</hi> they doe fight againſt GOD him ſelfe. The deuils haue not gotten the victory in heauen againſt the Angels, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their ſhall they get it in earth againſt the Church: Many Angels did fall, many mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church doe fall dayly: But as the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:5177:57"/> kingdom of Angels was neuer wholly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen, ſo the whole Church ſhall neuer be vanquiſhed. Hel may ſhake the earth, but not the heauens. The Church is not an earthly building, a building of Adam, a building of no other foundation then natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral: It is an heauenly building, whollie ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural and diuine, whereof, not man, but God him ſelfe is the foundation, and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: and the holy Ghoſt is the Architect which hath gathered together the liuely ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: This building is not made of men borne by nature, as the children of Adam; but of men made heauenlie, regenerate by grace, as the children of God. Faith which is the bond of the bodie of that Church, is aboue the heauen, the obiect of that faith, which is IESVS: Chriſt, Author of that regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doth appertain more to heauen by his diuine perſon, then to earth by that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main nature. Therefore a thowſand hels ſhal neuer be able to preuaile againſt that church whoſoeuer thou art therfore which haſt ſeparated thy ſelf from that Church, what ſo euer thing thou doeſt, thou art not apparteining to IESVS Chriſt: thou art a member of ſathan and a pray of euerlaſting damnation. Goe about the earth and the ſee, trott vp and downe the world, and goe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:5177:57"/> where thou wilt ſearching the truth, thou ſhalt not find the ſame out of this Church. The Church Catholike, Apoſtolike and Romain is the ſame of whom doth ſpring &amp; riſe as from a center, all the droctrine of Chriſtianitie; the chaire of S. Peter is the chaire of Ieſus Chriſt, and of the truth it ſelf, al other chaires are the chaires of peſtilence. Take away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before thy eyes thoſe clouds of euil opinions heaped together and thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened by falſe reportes againſt eccleſiaſticall perſons, and doe hinder the to ſee the truth, if there be any ſpottes in thoſe perſons which be ſett in the chaire of S. Peter, it muſt needes be that all the true children of God find them ſelues therby inwardlie wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and praye to God to make them cleane. But in the meane time what ſo euer they be in their maners, thoſe are particular matters perſonal, and ſeparated from the chaire, which is a dignitie, authoritie and matter vniuerſal. I know that in manie ther is not a cromme of the holines of S. Peter; &amp; that they be ſcandelouſlie gone a ſtraie from the life Apoſtolike, but they teach the faith of S. Peter &amp; the Apoſtolike doctrine. Looke not then vpon the faultes of the perſons: haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the promiſe and to the prayer of our ſauiour. If the defectes of the miniſters be of more force with the or beare more ſwaie
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:5177:58"/> with the, for to alienate the from the church, than the reuerence of the prayer and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſe of our ſauiour, to kepe the there; thow art vnwoorthie of any other prayer and promeſſe of our ſauiour. The chaire of S. Peter is the maiſtreſſe of the faith: I wold that ſhe were alſo the example of holie life. But what ſo euer ſcandal there hath bene in ſome, thou ſhalt find others in the prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and people, that better know the faults wherin they are, then thei ſelf: more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alſo, and leſſe reprocheable in their maners, and in all pointes leſſe imperfect then they ſelf: and are in ioye and in peace of their conſcience in this Church. There they receiue the ſacraments of life euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting they exerciſe the workes of charitie, and there attend the iudgement of God. Doe not ſay apart to thy ſelfe that thou doeſt worſhippe Ieſus Chriſt; that thou doeſt beleeue the Goſpel; and that thou doeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue thy ſelf according to the expreſſe word of God; euen ſo ſayd <hi>Arrius, Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus, Pelagius,</hi> and all the auncient heretikes: Thou doeſt not worſhip Ieſus: It is thy ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination and thy particular fanſie (wherof thou doeſt make an Idol) which thou doeſt worſhipe: Thou doeſt bowe thy ſelf downe before the woord of the deceiuer that hath
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:5177:58"/> ſeduced the; &amp; not before the woord of God: That which the Church doth teach, is the expreſſe woord of God: That which the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike doth teach, is the expreſſe woord of the deuil, which doth vſurp the iudgement of the expreſſe woord of God, and doth vſe the ſame for a baite, to make the ſwallow vp the hooke of error. This now is the verie grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of al ſynnes, for wheras al that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſay of the formalitie of ſinne, it is no other thing but the turning away and goyng farre of from God, There is no crime which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perateth more from God, than hereſie: and there is not a ſinner that Ieſus Chriſt doth hate ſo much, as the heretike. The ſinnes of workes, Adulterie, Meſlanghter, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and other, doe depriue men of the grace of God, but thei doe not driue a man from the Church, neither doe they cut away the roote of life which is the faith by the which a man may find the way to enter againe into grace: but hereſie doth not onlie take away grace, but doth alſo cut away the root of life, &amp; doth depriue men of the participatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all good things that be in the church. The ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſayth: <hi>that faith is the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thinges to hoped for: that without faith, it is impoſsible to pleaſe God: that the iuſte of God do liue by faith:</hi> that is
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:5177:59"/> to ſay breflie, that faith is the foundation of all Chriſtian building. Now hereſie doth take awaie from vs faith; then onlie hereſie is a ſufficient cauſe why the heretike can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wel ground his hope, can neuer doe worke agreable to God, nor can neuer haue the life of the iuſt of God. The other ſinnes be as a tyle taken from the couerture, or as a ſtone drawen from the wall, which doth much hurt to the building: But hereſie is as it were the vndermyning of the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which doth deſtroye the whole buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. To be ſhort, this kinde of argument is plaine and verie true, that no man can ſaue him ſelfe without the Sacraments of the Church: The Sacraments be not admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred but by the prieſt, the prieſtes be not made but by the Biſhoppes, Biſhoppes be not made but in the Romain Church, then what ſo euer thing that man doth, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible by all impoſſibilitie to ſaue him ſelf out of the Catholike, Apoſtolike and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Church. Doe not reſiſt thees argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: the more thou doeſt enforce they ſelf to auoide them by euaſions, ſo many more hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters doeſt thou put about thine owne neck, &amp; ſmiteſt the axe in to thine owne foot: And what ſo euer thy tounge doth ſpeake to the contrarie, thy ſoule doth fight againſt
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:5177:59"/> the: and thy conſcience ſhal neuer be in reſt, as longe as thou ſhalt be in hereſie.</p>
               <p>And S. Hierom vpon thoſe words of S. Paul; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hier. in epi. ad Tit. c.</hi> 3.</note> that an heretike is ſubuerted and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his owne proper iugement, ſayth verie wel thus, the fornicator, the adulterer, the manſlaer and other euil doers, be driuen out of the Church againſt their willes by the prieſtes: But the heretikes of them ſelues, without conſtraint do depriue them ſelues of the Sacraments of ſaluation, and of all the good things which be in the Church, damning them ſelues wittinglie, and throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them ſelues downe hedlonge from their proper fredome, in to the bottomleſſe pitt of euerlaſting perdition.</p>
               <p>For concluſion I will exhort the, as the Angels of God did exhort the handmaide <hi>Agar,</hi> that was departed with her ſonne from the houſe of <hi>Abraham,</hi> whom to bring home again, finding her in the wildernes taking the waie towardes <hi>Aegipt,</hi> he ſaied to her: poore il aduiſed Agar, ſeruant of <hi>Sara,</hi> from whence comeſt thou? and whether goeſt thou? tourne again to thy maiſtres, and humble thy ſelf vnder her hand: as if he wold ſay, thinke on thy eſtate, that thou comeſt from a noble houſe, riche, ful of the bleſſings of God: that thou goeſt to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:5177:60"/> caſt thy ſelf as a ſtrayed ſheepe into the throte of the woolf, in the land of malediction: And all theſe things well thought on, turne again to thy maiſtres: and humbling thy ſelf vnder her hand, thou ſhalt be happie in that houſe. Euen ſo will I ſay to euerie heretike, thinke that thou comeſt from the houſe of the lyuing God, which is the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, Apoſtolike, &amp; Romaine Church, in the which onlie is the grace of Ieſus Chriſt and the remiſſion of ſinnes, and all bleſſings of God: and thou goeſt in to the ſect of a deceiuer, which is one particuler man, by whoſe mouth ſathan hauing diuided the from the bodie of the only Church, it muſt neds folow that thou fall in to the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pitt of hereſie, which is the bottomleſſe pitt of death and euerlaſting damnation.</p>
               <p>Take then the exhortation of the Angel, comforter of <hi>Agar,</hi> if not, thou ſhalt ſoone mete an other Angel which ſhal be thy deſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>royer. <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.
<hi>Heb.</hi> 9.</note> If thou haſt erred vntil this tyme, cut the threde of thy errours: renounce hereſie, and all newnes of opinion; be the diſciple, not of any particular man what ſo euer he maye be, were he more holy and more elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent then an Angel, but only of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, the which can neuer erre; for ſo much as ſhe is gouerned by the holie
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:5177:60"/> Ghoſt; and that IESVS Chriſt is her head, which is the ſeur ground of the Catholikes: vnto the which I pray God giue vs the grace to cleaue, and continue firme and ſure, &amp; that we be found lyuelie members of his body, when we ſhal-be iudged.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>SO BE IT.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div n="original" type="license_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:5177:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Libellum hunc, Gallice intitulatum <hi>Du firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment des Catholiques contre l'Abiſme des heretiques</hi> fideliter è Gallico in Anglicanum idio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, per nobilem virum Joannem Pauncefote tranſlatum, ac per eximium Dominum Dom. Thomam Stapletonium Anglum, S. Theologiae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſorem examinatum ac manu eius propria appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum) Ac poſtremo ex primaria copia (manu dicti D. Stapletoni ſubſignata) fideliter (teſte venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili Domino <hi>D.</hi> wilhelmo Clederow Prefbytero Anglo) tranſſcriptum tuto poſſe imprimi, ac prelo committi praeſentium tenore atteſtor ego infraſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptus. Antwerpiae 9. Octob. Anno 1590.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Michael Hetſroey Bruegelius S. Theologiae Licentiatus Canonicus Cathedralis Eccleſiae B. Mariae Antwerpienſis, librorum Cenſor.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5177:61"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
